<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning the celibacy of the clergy</title>
            <author>R. H., 1609-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7162</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13713949</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13713949</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101527</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101527)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 855:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning the celibacy of the clergy</title>
                  <author>R. H., 1609-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Abraham Woodhead, whose works often appear under initials R.H.  Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101527:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101527:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE CONCERNING THE CELIBACY OF THE CLERGY.</p>
            <p>At OXFORD Printed, <hi>Anno</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:101527:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101527:2"/>
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> CElibacy a better ſtate than Marriage. §. <hi>1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A holineſs of the Body, as well as of the Soul. §. <hi>2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>As a holineſs of it, that is oppoſite to fornication; ſo that is oppoſite to Marriage. §. <hi>2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the married, on pious occaſions, forbearance of the acts of marriage adviſed. §. <hi>3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Forbearance of ſecond marriages commended; in ſome caſes, enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. §. <hi>4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Having a greater reward in the world to come. §. <hi>5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Continency eſpecially neceſſary for the Clergy. §. <hi>6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That it is the gift of God. §. <hi>7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Given to very many. §. <hi>8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For ſome ſpace of time, at leaſt, to all.</item>
               <item>That none, from not exerciſing the act of continency, can ſay, he hath not the power. §. <hi>9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That he, who, having this gift, doth not exerciſe it, in living unmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, ſinneth not. §. <hi>10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Whether the gift of Continency (ſuppoſing it to be given only to ſome) may by them be certainly known.</item>
               <item>That tho all have not, yet all may have, the gift of continency. And that God denies it none, at no time, they uſing the means. §. <hi>12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That it may be vowed. §. <hi>15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Yet it more difficult, than the matter of any other vow. §. <hi>25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Therefore not haſtily to be vowed. §. <hi>26.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Yet not unlawful for the Church, and very beneficial to reſtrain the ſacred function of the Miniſtry to ſingle perſons. §. <hi>27.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="quotations_of_authorities">
            <pb facs="tcp:101527:3"/>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ambroſ. de Viduis.</hi>
                  </bibl>
— Scit Creator omnium affectus eſſe varios ſingulorum; &amp; ideo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miis virtutem provocavit, non infirmitatem vinculis alligavit. — Sunt ſpadones, qui ſe caſtraverunt <hi>&amp;c:</hi> ſed hoc non omnibus imperatur, ſed ab omnibus flagitatur.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>—De Virginibus 3. l.</hi>
                  </bibl> —Dominus, qui ſciret praedicandam omnibus integritatem, imitandam paucis, Non omnes <hi>(in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit)</hi> capiunt verbum iſtud.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hierom contra Vigilantium 2. Ep.</hi>
                  </bibl>
—Exortus eſt ſubito <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> qui damnandas dicat eſſe vigilias, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> continentiam haereſin; pudicitiam, libidinis ſeminarium dicat <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (dicat) — proh nefas! Epiſcopos ſui dicitur ſceleris habere conſortes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> qui niſipraegnantes uxores viderint Clericorum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Chriſti Sacramenta nontribuunt. Quid facient Orientis Eccleſiae? Quid <hi>Aegypti,</hi> &amp; Sedis Apoſtolicae? Quae aut virgines Clericos accipiunt, aut continentes: aut, ſi uxores habuerint, mariti eſſe deſiſtunt.—</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Conc. Trident. Seſſ. 24.9. Can.</hi>
                  </bibl>
—Si quis dixerit, Clericos in ſacris Ordinibus conſtitutos poſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonium contrahere, non obſtante lege Eccleſiaſtica vel voto, —anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſit. cum Deus id <hi>[donum caſtitatis]</hi> recte petentibus non deneget, nec patiatur nos ſupra id quod poſſumus, tentari.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Bellarmin. de Clericis. 1.18. c.</hi>
                  </bibl>
—B. <hi>Thomas</hi> diſerte docet, votum continentiae eſſe annexum Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ſacris ex ſolo Eccleſie decreto, ac proinde diſpenſabile eſſe, —quod ego veriſſimum puto.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Again,</hi> ibid.</bibl> —In tota Scriptura nullum tale extat praeceptum, <hi>[viz. ut Sacerdotes non ducant uxores.]</hi>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>—Ib.</hi>
                  </bibl> —Eccleſia Romana multis jam ſaeculis permiſit Graecis ſacerdotibus uſum uxorum, quas ante Ordinationem duxerant, ut patet ex c. <hi>Cum olim de Clericis conjugatis.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101527:3"/>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>CONCERNING</hi> CELIBACY.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>1</label> I. IT muſt be granted, concerning <hi>Celibacy;</hi> That it is a <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> condition of life <hi>than Marriage,</hi> for prayer and faſting,<note place="margin">Celibacy a better ſtate than Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</note> and all other ſervice of God without diſtraction, and ſo for gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kingdom of Heaven (<hi>Matt.</hi> 19.12.); for works of charity to our neighbour; for avoiding covetouſneſs, worldly cares and impediments, (and this in all, not only in afflicted, times;) for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying our <hi>liberty,</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.4.) which, when we can have, we are <hi>rather to uſe</hi> it. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.21. See for theſe 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1, 8, 26, 32. to the 37, 38. —<hi>Lu.</hi> 14.20. —1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <p n="2">II. <hi>As there is a purity and holineſs of the body, as well as of the ſoul,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>2</label>(ſee 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. —1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.4. —<hi>Jud.</hi> 23. compared with 8. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10, 14) oppoſite to fornication and uncleanneſs,<note place="margin">A holines of the body as well as of the ſoul.</note> [which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs is more eſpecially oppoſed to holineſs than other vices, (ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.19. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.7. —<hi>Eph.</hi> 5.3.) and hath a natural ſhame and guilt upon it, which makes it ſeek privacy beyond any other ſin whatſoever; (ſee the ſhame of our Firſt Parents upon the firſt appearance of concupiſcence, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.25. compared with <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.10.)] and enjoyned to be obſerved in reference to Chriſt, he being now the husband of the body, and it his ſpouſe, (ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. compared with 13, 18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>):<note place="margin">As a holines of it that is oppoſite to fornication; ſo, that is oppoſite to marriage</note> 
                  <hi>ſo</hi> there ſeems to be <hi>a greater degree of this purity</hi> of the body <hi>oppoſite to Matrimony.</hi> See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.34. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4. where defilement with women is oppoſed to virginity, as another defilement is oppoſed to matrimony; <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.14. <hi>the marriage-bed is undefiled,</hi> that is, with ſin; (for this was appointed, as for a means of propagation to <hi>Adam</hi> innocent, ſo for a remedy againſt fornication (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2.) to man fallen, and troubled with
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101527:4"/>concupiſcence): yet the virgin's-bed, it ſeems, is more undefiled, more Angel-like in reſpect of corporeal purity: <hi>[undefiled]</hi> being oppoſed to an imperfection of chaſtity virginal, as well as to the ſin of luſt; to the act of concupiſcence, as well as to prohibited co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulations: therefore (hereafter) not to <hi>marry, nor be given in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, but to be like the Angels of God,</hi> is reckoned as a thing more honourable for the body. <hi>Lu.</hi> 20.35. And concupiſcence, one cauſe now of marriage, and which, could it be remedied, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle would not adviſe ſo many to marriage, was not known by <hi>Adam</hi> when perfect; and was a thing, when appearing upon his fall, which he was aſhamed of, and ſought to hide, as his poſterity ever ſince do, thoſe acts, even of the lawful bed. To a higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree (then) of this primogeneal virginal purity of the body I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that expreſſion relates, 1 Cor. 7.34. <hi>The virgin careth</hi> &amp;c. that <hi>ſhe may be holy both in body, and in ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>3</label> And for this reaſon it ſeems to be, that we find abſtinence from the acts of (if I may ſo call it) lawful luſt adviſed (for the better performance of holy duties,<note place="margin">To the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, on pious occaſions, forbearance, of the acts of marriage adviſed.</note> or in times of humiliation <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) even to thoſe, who are in the ſtate of marriage, (as doubtleſs conjugal chaſtity alſo hath many degrees in it, and in ſome men is far more pure than in others, and the permiſſions of matrimonial priviledges very eaſily tranſgreſſed. See <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.15. —three days ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and not coming at their wives; —1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.4. —women kept from them about three days, and the veſſels of the young men holy, <hi>i. e.</hi> from their wives; —<hi>Zech.</hi> 7.3. where we ſee, that, in times of more earneſt addreſſes to God, this ſeparation from car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality was continued. Neither is this only Old-Teſtament-cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial holineſs: but ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.5. a place parallel to theſe; <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud ye not one the other except it be with conſent for a time, that ye may give your ſelves to faſting and prayer.</hi> Where it may be noted, that as faſting hath no good correſpondence with the acts of the conjugal bed, <hi>(ſine Cerere &amp;c.)</hi> ſo theſe alſo are as prejudicial to faſting, and its companions. And ſutable to theſe Scriptures were the Decrees of the ancient Church: —<hi>Diebus orationis, &amp; jejunio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; praeparationis ad Euchariſtiam a conjuge abſtinendum.</hi> And this, becauſe carnal pleaſures are ſome way or other always ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to ſpiritual exerciſes; either proceeding to exceſs, and ſo rendring us faulty; or too much either heightening, or alſo debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litating our temper, and ſo making us undiſpoſed; or dividing, and diverting ſome portion of that love, and of thoſe intentions to things inferior, which are always all incomparably beſt ſpent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and conſecrated to, God the ſupreme good.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101527:4"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>4</label> Again, we find, after one marriage, the abſtaining from a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond both commended, (ſee <hi>Lu.</hi> 2.36) and, to ſome perſons, to wit,<note place="margin">Forbearance of ſecond marriages commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; in ſome caſes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined.</note> thoſe entertained in the pious or holy Services of God, or the Church, enjoyned: as appears in the <hi>widdows</hi> of the Church, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.9. of whom it is there required, that ſuch widdow <hi>have bin the wife of one man;</hi> which words being capable of ſeveral ſences, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ſhe have not had two husbands at once, or not two ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively; again, not two ſucceſſively, either by a divorce from the former, or upon the death of the former: ſeeing that no wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man might have two husbands at one time, nor any women at all were allowed remarrying upon divorce; (ſee 1 Cor. 7.11.) it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that the Apoſtle's widdow muſt be underſtood to be ſuch, as had not had a ſecond husband after the firſt dead. For this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction ſeems to have ſomething ſingular in it, the ſame caution being given no where to any, but only to Church-officers, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. Nor is it probable (as ſome againſt the current of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity interpret it) that the Apoſtle here reſtrained only the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſuch a widdow as had cauſleſly turned away her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and unlawfully married another man, (which is granted was done ſometimes, but ſeldom and without any permiſſion of <hi>Moſes</hi> law; (ſee <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.12) or, as had many husbands at the ſame time, (of which there are ſome <hi>rare</hi> examples amongſt the heathen,) becauſe ſuch things cannot well be imagined (tho poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) to have hapned in the Church; or when they hapned, not to have bin ſeverely puniſhed with excommunication; as we ſee the inceſtuous <hi>Corinthian</hi> was. And the Apoſtle ſeems here ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to require ſomething of extraordinary example and goodneſs above others, in ſuch as were thus to be devoted to the Churches Service, and maintained by her Charity, than only to caution, that they ſhould not be of the worſt wicked amongſt Chriſtians. Which is further confirmed by St. <hi>Paul's</hi> diſpleaſure againſt thoſe Church-widdows that remarryed, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. And if this interpretation be admitted for the widdows, much more may it, upon the like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion <hi>[a husband of one wife]</hi> for the Biſhops of the Church, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. and for the Deacons, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <p n="3">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>5</label> III. Tho <hi>Celibacy,</hi> as it occaſions larger fruits of righteouſneſs to many,<note place="margin">Having a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the world to come.</note> yet if a married condition alſo produceth the ſame, it hath no preheminence in this beyond wedlock: yet, as in it ſelf, it is a ſtronger reſiſtance of the luſting of the fleſh, and a greater ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duer of the natural concupiſcence, which all have leſs or more; whoſe importunities it heroically repelleth, whilſt the married
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101527:5"/>only lawfully ſatisfies them; thus, it <hi>ſeems worthy of,</hi> and ſo to have promiſed to it, <hi>a higher reward</hi> and crown <hi>in the world to come,</hi> and is one of the eminenteſt of all the virtues; as not moderat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but ſubduing the moſt violent of paſſions. See <hi>Eſai.</hi> 56.4, 5. where <hi>Eunuchs,</hi> who as <hi>dry trees</hi> under the law were much diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, (<hi>Deut.</hi> 23.1.) yet under the Goſpel have ample promiſes beyond thoſe who beget children. —See <hi>Matt.</hi> 19.12. where the Kingdom of heaven being inheritable without it, the uſing of this means ſeems to be for ſomething ſingular in that Kingdom, as well as for the more eaſie or certain attaining it. But however this be, thoſe who grant <hi>there</hi> ſeveral degrees of glory, propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to thoſe <hi>here</hi> of ſanctity, muſt give the higheſt to Virgins; becauſe if ſuppoſed only equal with the reſt in all other graces, they are granted in one to be ſuperior. See <hi>Act.</hi> 21.9. where <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin</hi> ſeems to be a term of honor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <p n="4">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>4</label>
                  <note place="margin">Continency eſpecially ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y or the Clergy.</note>IV. <hi>Single life,</hi> being ſo advantageous for having our liberty (freed from any other conjugal fetters) to beſtow our ſelves whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on Chriſt, and to wait upon him without diſtraction, freed from cares, and holy in body and ſpirit; ſeems, tho worthy to be ſought for by all, yet <hi>ſo neceſsary to none</hi> as to <hi>thoſe of the Clergy,</hi> ſo far as they find themſelves capable of it: that perfection, which others, as it were unneceſſitated thereto, attain by it, being their conſtant duty and profeſſion as it were; eſpecially, that; to <hi>give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto prayer,</hi> [1 Cor. 7.5. —Act. 6.4.] and <hi>to wait upon the Lord without diſtraction,</hi> [v. 35.] and to take <hi>a ſpecial care of the poor.</hi> Act. 6.3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <p n="5">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>5</label>
                  <note place="margin">That it is the gift of God.</note>
V. Tis plain, that this <hi>Continency,</hi> and the power of living a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle life, is <hi>the gift of God;</hi> both 1. ſuch a cool and moderate tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and calm paſſions as do not ſo eagerly provoke and kindle the fire of luſt in us; and 2ly. the grace to be able to abſtain and quench theſe fires, when we are provoked, if we will uſe the means; and 3ly. the actions or means, which we uſe, by them to procure the grace to abſtain, (as prayer, mortifications of the body, avoiding all temptations, conſtant and diligent employment,) are the gift of God. For ſo alſo are all other good things ſaid to be, both natural, and moral, and ſpiritual; even all thoſe things which we have moſt in our power, and which our induſtry moſt procures; and the powers themſelves, and every action of them. So, to be rich, to be honourable; the condition of a free-man, or of a ſervant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are the gift of God. <hi>See</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.17. —<hi>Deut.</hi> 8.17,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101527:5"/>18. —<hi>.3.27.</hi> And if we cannot, of our ſelves think a good thought, much leſs refrain the moſt violent of our luſts, except from the gift of the Almighty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <p n="6">VI. Taking this ability to contain,<note place="margin">§. 8 n. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Given to very m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> not for a power of being freed from all concupiſcence, and from the firſt motions of luſt; (for ſo none at all have this power,) but for a power to ſuppreſs theſe firſt motions, and quench theſe leſſer ſparks, before they break out into a flame, 1. either into fornication, therefore [<hi>v.</hi> 2.] <hi>marriage</hi> is oppoſed to <hi>fornication,</hi> as it is [<hi>ver.</hi> 9.] to <hi>burning;</hi> or, 2ly. into uncleanneſs, [<hi>which uncleanneſs, contradiſtinct from forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, is no ſmall guilt, but every where marcheth along with it as its fellow in the catalogue of thoſe ſins that exclude us from heaven,</hi> (<hi>ſee</hi> Gal. 5.19. Eph. 5.3. Col. 3.5. 2 Cor. 12.21. <hi>&amp;c. ſome kinds of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs being advanced above any other ſin, except that</hi> in Spiritum Sanctum; <hi>ſee</hi> 2 Pet. 2.10. Rom. 1.24. Eph. 4.18, 19. Rev. 22.15.] or 3ly. into moroſe delectation, ſomenting firſt, and heating our ſelves by it, before we put it out, [ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9. expounded by the 2.] in reſpect of which, virginal continency in ſeveral perſons is leſs or more pure: <hi>This power,</hi> I ſay, thus underſtood, (<hi>i. e. of being able to contain,</hi> if they be not wanting to themſelves,) <hi>is given to very many;</hi> nay, <hi>for ſome time at leaſt,</hi> to <hi>every one.</hi> For this I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe granted; that whenever marriage, or the uſe of it, is una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably hindered, or by God himſelf alſo prohibited, there alſo is given by him the power to contain. And this happens in very many inſtances; before, in, and after, marriage.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <p>For 1. before marriage,<note place="margin">§. 8. n. 2. For ſome ſpace of time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> leaſt, to All</note> there being many ceremonies to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in it, many ſurprizals of luſt ſeize upon youth that are more liable to it, when in an unripe age (of 12, 13, 14, years old per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps), which for the preſent, that way, cannot be remedied, who many times may not marry without the licenſe of their Superiors; as it happens to youth yet under the power of their parents, (to whom the Apoſtle allows a power in <hi>diſpoſing</hi> of them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.36. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and tis there to be noted, that he conſiders much more the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's inclinations, towards her ſingle life, or marriage, than the virgins); and to ſervants, not yet made free from their Maſters. Beſides that, many other cauſes of delaying marriage may inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene, as when it is not permitted to any at certain times of the year ſet aſide for humiliation; <hi>Lent, &amp;c:</hi> So, when external im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments occur; as being in a journey, or impriſoned, or upon the Sea, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> and in many other caſes; and theſe happening moſt-what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101527:6"/>in the age too wherein concupiſcence is in its greateſt ſtrength; here, if ſome have not the power of continency, nor yet of the remedy, marriage, how will incontinency become a guilt?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">§. 8. n. 3.</note> Again, in the ſtate of marriage, there is neceſſary power of continency always required in reſpect of concupiſcence toward any perſon whatſoever (notwithſtanding the many temptations the world preſents) ſaving one, <hi>i. e.</hi> his wife; and toward all ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, when any ſicknes happens to that one party, to which we are confined; or when any caſual debility, tho never recoverable; ſo alſo, in all neceſſary abſence about the affairs of life, in journeys, in being taken captive by the <hi>Turks,</hi> or others, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> we muſt allow this gift. Els how can husbands, when buſied abroad by employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, embaſſies, warfares, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> be ſecure of the honeſty of their wives? or how can the State, who many times permit not their wives to follow them, lawfully make ſuch a ſeparation, by which they ſhall neceſſitate them to ſin? So, when the woman is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous, and after child-birth, before ſhe is churched, at leaſt to thoſe that were under <hi>Moſes</hi> his law. See <hi>Lev.</hi> 18.19. —20.18. <hi>Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c.</hi> 18.6. which abſtinence in the birth of a maid-child was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined for <hi>eighty</hi> days, almoſt a quarter of the year. See <hi>Lev.</hi> 12.5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">§. 8. n. 4.</note> And ſo after marriage diſſolved, we muſt allow this gift to all that are (juſtly or unjuſtly) divorced, who are prohibited under pain of adultery a ſecond contract, all or moſt of them; to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; to the widdows fore-named. Add to this; that of thoſe that marry, few (if we examin things well) do it, becauſe they want the power of continency, but for other reaſons; as appears, in many forbearing marriage, as long as their places or other ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar reſpects conſiſt not with it; and preſently, when quit of theſe, engaging in it: and in moſt, wedding after the heat and concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence of their youth is already in the wane and declination. And when we ſee ſo many, without marrying, at length reclaimed from former vitious courſes, and becoming in a ſingular manner conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, we have reaſon to preſume, that God was not wanting to them, in affording the like power to them before; but they rather wanting to the grace of God, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>9</label>
                     <note place="margin">That none from not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the act of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>n ſay, he hath not the ſew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> and to themſelves.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <p n="7">VII. Since many that certainly have from God the power to contain, (as the divorced, the one party when the other is debili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) yet do not, or with ſome difficulty (yea more than the never-married have, becauſe otherwiſe accuſtomed,) and not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101527:6"/>without temptations to the contrary, do, contain; <hi>none can gather</hi> (neither the delinquent, or others) <hi>from not containing, or from ſome difficulty therein, that he hath not power from God to contain,</hi> unleſs alſo he uſe the means; nor, in uſing the means, can he certainly know it yet, unles certain that he hath uſed all the means, and in that manner theſe as he ought; (hence none can ſay, that any of thoſe, who, vowing chaſtity, proved afterward incontinent, had not power to contain;) or if he perceiveth that as yet he hath not the power, yet knows he not, whether for the future he may receive it; as many do, that of debauch'd, without marriage, at length become chaſt. Therefore can none gather from an act of unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or fornication committed by him, that he cannot have the gift of continency for the future; or that abſolutely from one ſuch experience of himſelf he is obliged to marry. But it remains ſtill true concerning him, as well as others; that, as it is <hi>melius nubere, quam uri;</hi> ſo tis <hi>melius continere, quam nubere;</hi> if then at length he ſhall ſeriouſly attempt to quench ſuch burning with prayers, ſolitude, faſting, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> the prime and more noble, rather than by wedlock, the ſecond, and much inferior, remedy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <p n="8">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>10</label>
                  <note place="margin">That he who having this gift doth not exerciſe it in living un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth not.</note>VIII. It ſeems, <hi>that he that hath, and yet doth not exerciſe, the gift of Continency, nor practiſe our Saviours precept or advice of Celiba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> Matt. 19.12. <hi>doth not ſin in ſo doing.</hi> For then marrying, to ſome perſons, would be a ſin. Which 1. the Apoſtle ſaith, it is not, even to thoſe, whom, upon the gift of continency, he adviſeth to Celibacy. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.27, 28, 36, 38. —and <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.4. 2. If it were; it would follow, (ſince there is no divorcement upon any ſuch title,) that there would be a ſin which a man was bound to live in, and having committed it once, to commit it always; and whether would not the children here alſo be illegitimate, where the marrying is unlawful. 3. Then Celibacy can be recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to no perſons in reſpect of any times of diſtreſs, (as <hi>yet</hi> we find it was by the Apoſtle 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.26.) ſince, after puberty, all men ſin, either in marrying, or els in abſtaining: for thoſe who have not the gift of continency in the moſt afflicted times, ought to marry; and the other, in the moſt proſperous, to forbear. 4. Thoſe,<note place="margin">Whether the gift of continency (ſuppoſing it to be g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>me) can by them &amp;c certainly known.</note> whom ſuch ſuppoſed precept of Celibacy ſhould oblige, muſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way certainly know it; els how can they either forbear, or repent of, a ſin, which they know not when they commit. And, as ſoon as they know it, they are bound, either preſently to marry, if they find they have not the gift of continency; or for ever to abſtain, if they have: ſo that thoſe who marry not, as ſoon as capable of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101527:7"/>marriage, and marry afterward, either ſin in marrying then, or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in not marrying before. 5. But how any one can certainly know this gift in him, I ſee not. Firſt, by what ſigns ſhall he know if he hath it? In being free from temptation? So none is. In over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming them? But who foreknows the ſucceſs of future conflicts? May not he marry then, if much tempted, to prevent ſinning? May he not marry, unless he firſt burn? But then in marrying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore burning, perhaps he hath the gift; and ſo ſins in marrying. But if by the effect only of reſiſting, or yeilding to, a temptation, we know the gift; it follows, that none can know he wants the gift, but by (at leaſt once) ſinning, yet, to prevent which ſin none may, firſt, marry. 2. Again, how ſhall he know if he have not this gift? by burning or any one act of any uncleanneſs? 1. None can argue from not exerciſing the act of continency, that he hath not the power, (as is ſhewed before §. 9.) till he knows whether this failing proceeds from the abſence, or from his own ill manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of God's gift. For that it oft proceeds from our ill husbandry of grace, is manifeſt in many of thoſe mentioned before §. 7. who having certainly from God the power to contain, yet are many times very incontinent. If in this caſe therefore he ſhould go and marry, having the gift, but abuſing it, what <hi>thus</hi> would this be, but a multiplying of ſins, the ſin of luſt begetting the ſin of wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock? 2. If thus, after any ſuch uncleanneſs, all (as being denied the gift of continency) were obliged to marry, then all, who remain not in a pure virginity, would be ſinners in a ſingle life.</p>
               <p>But then;<note place="margin">§. 11. n. 1.</note> theſe are likewiſe fit things to be known; whether the gift once had may not aferward be withdrawn? for if ſo; at ſeveral times, to the ſame perſon to marry, or live ſingle, may be a ſin. Again, whether not being given at firſt, it may be given af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward? for then, after ſome act of incontinency we need not caſt our ſelves preſently into the bonds of marriage; upon the hopes we have, from our prayers <hi>&amp;c,</hi> of recovering this gift: neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is every one by the Apoſtle, after burning, bound to marry, (unleſs he find himſelf refractory, and unwilling to uſe the means to quench ſuch burning, as well as to remove all occaſions of this flame, apt from his temper, temptations, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> continually to break out again,) becauſe he is not by this certain, that for the future he may not by the grace, and other means uſed, be freed from ever falling again into this fire. Since many, after ſuch burning, have attained, without marrying, to the higheſt degree of Continency. As S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> after long incontinency, received this gift, ſo ſoon as he humbly, and earneſtly, and mortifiedly ſought it.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101527:7"/>
               <p>Now if this once be granted from what is premiſed;<note place="margin">§. 11. n. 2.</note> that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to no perſon (I mean in relation to his power to contain) is a ſin, nor celibacy to any abſolutely neceſſary; it follows, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's advice <hi>Matt.</hi> 19.12. is not a precept or command of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute duty to any, under pain of ſinning if he not obſerve it; but only a Counſel of greater perfection, under the penalty (if I may ſo ſay) hereafter of a leſs reward if he not practiſe it. (See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6.) Note, that by <hi>counſel</hi> or <hi>precept of perfection,</hi> (where-ever this expreſſion is found referring to <hi>celibacy, abandoning of riches, &amp;c,</hi>) I mean this: The adviſing us of, and to, a means, whereby we may, more eaſily, and free from impediments, attain the dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of ſin, and the increaſe of virtue and grace in us; in which greater purity from ſin, and greater practice of holy duties and habits of grace, and not in the means preſcribed, conſiſts that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of perfection, to which we by this means attain: which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection alſo may, poſſibly, but not ſo eaſily, be acquired without it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <p n="9">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>12</label>
                  <note place="margin">That tho all have no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, yet all may have, the gift of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency: and that God denies it to none, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> no time, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> no time, they uſing the means.</note>IX. Next: It ſeems alſo, to be a <hi>counſel</hi> or <hi>precept</hi> of greater per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, not only to ſome particular perſons, (as ſome others in the next place would limit it,) but <hi>to all;</hi> and that, tho every one hath not, (<hi>Matt.</hi> 19.11.) yet <hi>every one may have this gift of Continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> (and ſo may practiſe the precept or counſel of celibacy) <hi>if he</hi> pleaſe to <hi>uſe</hi> thoſe <hi>means</hi> and endeavours, upon which God gives it; and that every one may make himſelf an Eunuch, if he pleaſe, for the kingdom of heaven. (1). For, firſt, were it a ſingular gift gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitally given only to ſome men; then, as we have ſhewed before, that it is neceſſary for thoſe, to whom we hold it is given as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of duty, by ſome ſigns certainly to diſcern it, for their avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſin; ſo tis neceſſary alſo to theſe to whom we hold it is given as a counſel of perfection, to know it, for their endeavouring to do that which may more pleaſe God; that ſuch gracious gifts may not be beſtowed in vain, and their ſalvation ſuffer much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment; if men endeavour not, or their endeavour be not only in vain, but diſpleaſing to God, <hi>ne quis incontinentia laborans, dum coelibatum appetit, cum Deo luctetur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Calvin;</hi> and expoſing them to ſin, if God give not.</p>
               <p>Now the difficulties of diſcerning any ſuch thing, ſee before: yet without diſcerning which (unleſs all be capable of this gift) there can be no alacrity in our endeavours; nor will any labour to make themſelves Eunuchs. Eſpecially, when one ſees any evident ſigns, or alſo hath once felt the effects of incontinency, none ſhould dare any further to defer marriage, or any further entertain any
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101527:8"/>endeavour of attaining this gift contrary to ſuch indications of God's denial of it to him; yet is this much contrary to the practice of many holy men. (2.) There ſeems no ſufficient reaſon, to make this grace, which is converſant about the ſtrongeſt of all paſſions, and the very root of ſin; upon which depend ſo many excellent advantages in ſerving God <hi>&amp;c,</hi> (confeſs'd by all,) and granted alſo to be given to all, at all times, when the remedy of marriage cannot (as often it can not) be had; to make this grace, I ſay, when there is opportunity of marrying, then only, a gratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ital grace given to ſome; others being denied it, tho never ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt after it. And thus to reſtrain this grace, only upon ſuch a pretence, becauſe tho denied the gift of continency, they have a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs way of ſatisfying their concupiſcence: when as indeed this appointed remedy of marriage (as it refers to incontinency, not to progeny) may argue only the difficulty in ſome, not the impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in any, of attaining this gift; and, being inſtituted for a help of our weakneſs, ought not to be made an argument of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of God's goodneſs and bounty. Again; no reaſon, to make this prace only particular to ſome few; when as all other graces whatſoever, converſant about the like object, <hi>i. e.</hi> the moderating and ſubduing of our paſſions, are proclaimed to be general; and all men capable of them, who are not wanting to God and themſelves. So we do not ſay that any are neceſſitated to be immoderate in meat, or drink, or ſleep, in the love of riches, or honor, but, upon doing their endeavour, grace ſufficient to be given to all, to bridle the appetite, and maſter the affections; only the extremities of concupiſcence it is that we affirm ſome men are diſ-enabled upon any means whatſoever to ſuppreſs. When as mean-while it muſt be granted, that to thoſe ſingular favorites, to whom God pleaſeth to give it, it is, both gotten by means; elſe why are any ſaid to make themſelves <hi>Eunuchs?</hi> and preſerved by means: for none that have the gift (as thoſe who in marriage have their bedfellows ſick or abſent) are free from temptations, and do only by means and reſiſtance overcome them; which means experience ſhews to be powerful, not only for ſubduing luſt in men, but in the brute beaſts alſo. Whereas therefore there are two ſorts of God's gifts to us; 1. ſome to the obtaining of which is required our endeavour joyned or ſubſervient to God's both preventing and aſſiſting grace, or aid; ſuch as are <hi>Faith, Hope, Charity, Patience,</hi> &amp;c. which, tho always God s gifts, yet may be ſaid in ſome ſenſe to be in our power alſo, in as much as we are to preſume, that God denies them to none, by his aid rightly firſt ſeeking and labouring for them. 2. Others
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101527:8"/>given <hi>gratis</hi> by him without any cooperation of ours, (tho we may alſo deſire and pray for them. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.1.) Note that there is not any other of thoſe uſually called <hi>gratiae gratis datae,</hi> (which are divided to every man as the Spirit pleaſeth, mentioned 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.) any way like unto this of continency. 1. They being not conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant about paſſions, or bettering our ſelves, but edifying and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting others. 1 Cor. 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 7.— 2. Not by our means procured, or conſerved, but conferred without our cooperation or endeavor; therefore we find no exhortations to the practice of them, as if they were in our power, as we find to continency: 1 Cor. 7. We find it not ſaid concerning them, <hi>There be Prophets that have made themſelves Prophets,</hi> or, —<hi>He that can receive them, let him receive them.</hi> 3. Thoſe who have them ſinning, if they be not uſed: the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of which is proved in continency. 4. Laſtly, neither is there any thing ſaid of continency, as reſtraining it to ſome particular perſon; which is not ſaid of thoſe other gifts, and graces of God of the firſt kind, as particularly of that of Faith. See 23. §. (3). Concerning the other great precepts or counſels for attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perfection, as that in particular by quitting ſuperfluous riches (and ſo by this, all the cares and temptations of them,) (of which may be ſaid, what is ſaid of marrying, 1 Cor. 7.34. and <hi>v.</hi> 30, 31. compared with 29. —2 Tim. 2.4.) ſo often recommended, See Matt. 19.21. preſently after the recommending of continency, <hi>v.</hi> 12. and both of them to be done for the Kingdom of Heaven. See likewiſe Lu. 12.33. Lu. 3.11.—6.35. —Matt. 5.42. —Lu. 16.9.11. —Matt. 19.29. compared 27. (where, as we muſt grant, that, tho marriage be lawful, yet the continent doth better; ſo, tho poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of riches is lawful, yet he that parts with, and beſtows, moſt of wealth ſuperfluous upon the poor, doth better, than he that keeps or ſpends more of it upon himſelf:) Concerning this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, I ſay, we do not contend, but that all are capable of receiving it: and yet our Saviour, upon occaſion of the young man's not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving ſo hard a ſaying, and ſo difficult a leſſon, ſeems to put the ſame difficulty in it, as in continency: for when he breaks out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, [<hi>verily I ſay a rich man ſhall hardly enter into the kingdom</hi> &amp;c. and again, <hi>Camels ſhall as eaſily be threaded thro Needles,</hi> ver. 23, 24. ſee 1 Cor. 1.26.] he ſaith only, (if we well obſerve,) It is hard for rich men to receive this ſaying, <hi>[go and ſell,] i. e.</hi> of parting with their ſuperfluous wealth. For, be this hardneſs of rich mens en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into heaven, from their truſting in their riches, or from hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continual temptations of exceſs, and fuell for all their luſts mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by wealth; or from continual cares and diſtractions from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101527:9"/>them, Matt. 13.22. (which alſo he names, from marriage, 1 Cor. 7.35): all is preſently remedied in receiving this ſaying, (yet foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh men take no notice of it,) <hi>ſell that ye have,</hi> [i. e. <hi>ſuperfluous,</hi>] <hi>and give it away in almes,</hi> (where the charity is not ſo much to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as to our ſelves.) For in parting with his riches, he is ſure at once to part with his truſt in them, cares, temptations of them, <hi/> for no man truſts in, or is tempted with, what he hath not. I have ſtayed the longer upon this general offer of the gift of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency on God's part; becauſe the conceit of it as of a private gift is very diſcouraging (as we ſee by their practiſes, where this doctrine is taught,) for the attempting that heavenly condition of life (ſo much recommended by our Saviour, and St. <hi>Paul</hi>) after they firſt believe, that for ſome men no means can procure it; and then, by the ſtrong aſſaults of their luſts (from which none are free) believe that themſelves are ſuch. And hence, whilſt we are in ſuſpence, whether there be a poſſibility of it, or no, in reſpect of us, (as there is to none a poſſibility, who are deſtitute of the gift) we caſt all our care, not upon mortifying and refraining our luſt; but upon the obſervance of the Symptoms of this gift, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral riſings and heights of our luſts, accordingly to ſhape to our ſelves that future condition of life, to which our preſent ſeems to lead us. And all this without cauſe, whereas we may make our ſelves what we are not; and God's providing a remedy for an innocent ſatisfying of that concupiſcence, which cannot (by our deficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) otherwiſe be allayed, was by reaſon of our ordinary weakneſs, not of our abſolute neceſſity; to whom he (in ſome times) indulg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a facile changing alſo of thoſe to whome men were joyned: but it likewiſe not for their neceſſity, but for the <hi>hardneſs of their hearts.</hi> Matt. 19.8. —Whereas now it is a fruit of the Evangelical perfection, that husbands (by mutual conſent) do ſeparate from their wives (without taking others) for the Kingdom of God, (<hi>Lu.</hi> 18.29. compared 28.) always ſecure of the gift of continency from God, (if reſolute in their endeavours of preſerving it): Elſe this would be an act moſt unlawful, which our Saviour makes ſo heroical, and promiſeth to it ſo great a reward.</p>
               <p>It ſeems therefore, that God, this gift being ſo advantageous to his ſervice, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>13</label>(ſee <hi>parag.</hi> 1.) and ſo common, (ſee <hi>par.</hi> 7.) not denied upon repentance and prayer <hi>&amp;c</hi> to many grievous ſinners, after long contrary habits, without their uſing the remedy of marriage; that God, I ſay, denies not this power to any at all, who firſt have power over their own will; decree and ſtand ſtedfaſt in their heart;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101527:9"/>1 Cor. 7.37. reſolutely undertake and offer this their ſingleneſs to God for ſuch an end, as is ſo much approved by him; and then practiſe alſo the means conducing to it, which are obſerved (as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinency, for example,) naturally to cure the burnings of luſt, even in brute beaſts.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>14</label> Which thing to confirm yet further, both from the Scriptures, and from the primitive times of the Church: firſt, had God denied this gift to any, [1.] it ſeems that St. <hi>Paul</hi> could not juſtly have blamed the widdows, when ſome of them young, for remarrying; whoſe marriage, he ſaith, was out of <hi>wantonneſs,</hi> and that <hi>they had damnation, for having caſt off their firſt faith</hi> and promiſe, (<hi>i. e.</hi> of liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſingle, and attending wholly to thoſe charitable duties <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) which they had made to Chriſt, and the Church: but if God had not given them the power of obſerving their vow, the Apoſtle ſhould have allowed their remarrying, and blamed their vowing; who ordered alſo for the future, that ſuch young women ſhould no more be admitted to ſuch vows or duties, for publick ſervice of the Church; not becauſe they could not, but ordinarily would not, abſtain.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <p n="2">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>15</label>[2.] Neither would our Saviour have recommended the like reſolution and attempt, in thoſe, who, he ſaith, <hi>made themſelves Eunuchs for the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Matt. 19.12. if he would not alſo be aſſiſtant to them with his grace; as he approved their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and deſign; to which alſo they were allured by his <hi>Encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums</hi> of that happier condition. Nor would he have (and that in the general) commended thoſe, who leave the pleaſures of marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age for the Kingdom of God's ſake, that is, for the better ſerving God in any way, (ſee 1 Cor. 7.34, 35.) or, thoſe who have forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their wives, (<hi>i. e.</hi> by mutual conſent, 1 Cor. 7.4, 5.) ſee Lu. 18.29. compared with Matt. 19.29. <hi>There is none that hath left,</hi> (or, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one, that hath forſaken,) <hi>wife</hi> &amp;c. <hi>who ſhall not receive</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken,</hi> i. e. as the Apoſtles did, in local ſeparation from them, (ſee Matt. 19.27.) unleſs continency were a gift; which all pious pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, uſing the means for conſerving it, and intending God's glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in it, may preſume upon. Tho, where we do not ſubdue our luſt, S. <hi>Paul</hi> as much prohibits any long ſeparation, as our Saviour here encourageth it. See 1 Cor. 7.5.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <p n="3">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>16</label>[3.] Neither would S. <hi>Paul</hi> have approved the ſame reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in thoſe, who could maſter ſo far their own will: 1 Cor.7.37. who doubtleſs, what he praiſeth in the father, (who yet might be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101527:10"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101527:10"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101527:11"/>neceſſitated to go againſt his will, by the virgin's incontinacibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) he would much more have approved in the virgin. Neither is that <hi>need</hi> (<hi>ver.</hi> 36.) neceſſity abſolute, as appears by what follows, <hi>[do what he will,]</hi> the <hi>other doing better.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <p n="4">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>17</label>[4.] The prohibition likewiſe in the primitive times, (tho not in all Churches, that no married perſon might be admitted to ſacred Orders, or, that every one, upon theſe received, muſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from his wife, yet) that none ſingle, when entring into ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Orders, (I mean of Prieſthood) might afterward marry, ſhews the perſwaſion of Antiquity to be; either that continency was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to none uſing the means, <hi/> or elſe, that, it being a ſpecial gift only to ſome, every one, before taking Orders, or making a Vow, might certainly know, not only, whether he had the gift for the preſent, but whether he might alſo perſevere therein to his death, (foraſmuch as concerned God the Doner thereof.) But here it is unintelligible, how ſuch aſſurance can ariſe, only to ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons; nor can any direct, how ſuch a ſpecial gift, not only for the preſent, but the future alſo, may be diſcerned. Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while concerning the prohibitions and practice of Antiquity, ſee and compare together <hi>Can. Apoſtol.</hi> 27. —<hi>Conc. Chalcedon. can.</hi> 13.15. —<hi>Conſtantinop. in Trullo. can.</hi> 6.12, 13. compared <hi>Can. Apoſt.</hi> 6: In brief, you will find the iſſue to be much-what to this purpoſe: That no Presbyter may marry after his taking Orders, nor Biſhop after his Conſecration: That of thoſe who, being before married, are admitted afterward into holy Orders, ſome Churches required that they ſhould ever after (by mutual conſent, [which was known before Orders conferr'd]) abſtain from their wives; as the Roman-Church: Some, that Biſhops only ſhould abſtain univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally; and ſimple Presbyters, only abſtain then when they were to officiate; as the Greek Church. —See likewiſe Provincial Councils celebrated about the time of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved afterwards by the <hi>Conſtant. Conc. in Trullo. can.</hi> 2. —<hi>Ancy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran. Conc. can.</hi> 10. —<hi>Neocaeſar. can.</hi> 1:—&amp;c,</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>18</label> But I think it beſt, for ſaving the labour of ſeeking, to ſet you down ſome of them: which you will find ſo clear, as that I think nothing can be replied to them. —<hi>Apoſtol. Canon.</hi> 27. <hi>In nuptiis autem qui ad Clerum evecti ſunt, Praecipimus ut, ſivoluerint, uxores acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piant, ſed lectores cantoreſque tantummodo;</hi> not the higher Orders of <hi>Biſhop, Presbyter, Deacon,</hi> &amp;c. —<hi>Conc. Ancyranum</hi> (before the firſt Council of <hi>Nice</hi>) <hi>Can.</hi> 10. —<hi>Diaconi quicunque cum ordinantur, ſi in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101527:11"/>ipſa ordinatione proteſtati ſunt, dicentes, velle ſe habere uxores, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> poſſe ſe continere,</hi> (where <hi>poſſe</hi> is taken as expounded §. 24.) <hi>hi poſtea ſi ad nuptias venerint, maneant in miniſterio, propterea quod his Epiſcopus licentiam dederit. Quicunque ſane tacuerunt &amp; ſuſceperunt manus impoſitionem, profeſſi continentiam, ſi poſtea ad nuptias venerint, a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterio ceſſare debebunt.</hi> [But note, that, <hi>ſi proteſtati ſunt,</hi> is here ſaid of Deacons only.] —<hi>Conc. Naeocaeſar.</hi> (before <hi>Nice</hi>) <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n.</hi> 1. —<hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter ſi uxorem duxerit, ab ordine ſuo illum deponi debere.</hi> —<hi>Conc. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caenum can.</hi> 3. —<hi>Omnibus modis interdixit ſancta Synodus; neque E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopo, neque Presbytero,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>omnino licere habere ſecum mulierem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traneam, niſi forte ſit mater, aut ſoror, aut avia, aut amita, vel mater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera. In his namque ſolis perſonis, &amp; harum ſimilibus omnis, quae ex mulieribus eſt, ſuſpicio declinatur.</hi> Whereas might they have enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a wife, neither would there have bin cauſe of ſuch ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion; nor would it have bin reaſonable, nor ſafe, to deprive their wives of all Women-attendance or Society. As for the ſtory of <hi>Paphnutius</hi> in this Council, [which makes ſo great a noiſe amongſt us; ſo that this inſtance ſtands for a bulwark againſt all the other evidence, in this point, of Antiquity, (ſee <hi>Calvin Inſtitut.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 26. and generally all our writers,)] this is the All of it: That, motion being made by ſome in the Council, that the married Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, (<hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch as were married before made Presbyters) ſhould after their Ordination be ſeparated from their wives: [which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration the Greek Church allows not to this day; and of which the 6th of thoſe called <hi>Canons Apoſtolical,</hi> ſaith thus, (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the ſame Canons prohibit marriage after Ordination ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to <hi>Lectores &amp; Cantores:</hi>) <hi>Epiſcopus aut Presbyter uxorem propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am nequaquam ſub obtentu religionis abjiciant:</hi> (Some conceive this to be meant, *without her conſent; others, * not for cohabitation, but for maintenance only:) <hi>Si vero rejecerit, excommunicetur.</hi>—And <hi>Concil. Gangrenſe,</hi> becauſe ſome held it unlawful to receive the Communion from a Presbyter formerly married, was neceſſitated to make this Canon. 4. —<hi>Quicunque diſcernit, a Presbytero, qui uxorem habuit,</hi> (here tis <hi>habuit,</hi> not <hi>habet,</hi>) <hi>quod non oporteat eo mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strante de oblatione percipere, Anathema ſit.</hi>] That, ſuch a motion being made, I ſay, <hi>Paphnutius,</hi> a Reverend Biſhop, and a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, tho never married, withſtood it, ſaying, <hi>Grave jugum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>neque a ſingulorum uxoribus fortaſſe eam castimoniae normam poſſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vari.</hi> But now mark what follows: —<hi>Illud ſatis eſſe, ut qui in Clerum ante aſcripti erant quam duxiſſent uxores, hi ſecundum veterem Eccleſiae Traditionem deinceps a nuptiis ſe abſtinerent; non tamen quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ab illa quam jampridem, cum laicus erat, uxorem duxiſſet, ſejungi
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101527:12"/>debere.</hi> The ſtory is in <hi>Socrates Eccl. Histor.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> and in others from him. <hi>Sozomen.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> Judg now what cauſe there is, to urge <hi>Paphnutius</hi> for the marrying of the Clergy, after H. Orders received by them when as ſingle. I go on. —<hi>Conc. Romanum</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Silveſter,</hi> in the time alſo of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, <hi>Can.</hi> 7. —<hi>Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum autem Subdiaconorum ad nuptias tranſire praecipimus, ne aliquam praevaricationem ſumpſerit.</hi> —<hi>Elibertin. Concil.</hi> about the ſame time in <hi>Spain;</hi> Can. 33. <hi>Placuit in totum prohibere Epiſcopis, Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteris, Diaconis, ac Subdiaconis, poſitis in miniſterio, abſtinere ſe a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugibus ſuis, &amp; non generare ſilios. Quod quicunque fecerit, ab honore Clericatus exterminetur.</hi> Which Canon plainly ſhews; That at that time in the Weſtern, tho not in the Eaſtern, Churches, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly marriage after Holy Orders was forborn, but abſtinence from their wives, by thoſe who were married before, was commonly practiſed; ſince he, who ſhould do the contrary, was ſo highly puniſhed. —<hi>Conc. Arelatenſe ſecundum</hi> under the ſame <hi>Silveſter.</hi> Can. 2. — <hi>Aſſumi aliquem in Sacerdotium in vinculo conjugii conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, niſi fuerit praemiſſa converſio, non oportet.</hi> Two Councils, in which S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> was preſent, * 1. <hi>Conc. Carthag.</hi> 2. Can. 2. —<hi>Placuit &amp; condecet ſacro-ſanctos Antiſtites &amp; Dei Sacerdotes, necnon &amp; Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> Deacons <hi>&amp;c, continentes eſſe in omnibus</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ut quod Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li docuerunt, &amp; ipſa ſervavit antiquitas, nos quoque cuſtodiamus. Ab univerſis Epiſcopis dictum eſt, omnibus placet, ut Epiſcopi, Presbyteri,</hi> &amp;c, <hi>pudicitiae cuſtodes etiam ab uxoribus ſe abſtineant.</hi> Hence S. <hi>Austin,</hi> (<hi>Confeſſ.</hi> 10. <hi>l.</hi> 30. <hi>c.</hi>) ſpeaking of his continency, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obliged by Prieſthood to it, ſaith, —<hi>Et quoniam dedisti factum est, &amp; antequam diſpenſator Sacramenti tui fierem.</hi> And *2. <hi>Conc. Africanum cap.</hi> 37. —<hi>Praeterea cum de quorundam Clericorum quamvis erga uxores proprias incontinentia referretur; placuit Epiſcopos, &amp; Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteros, &amp; Diaconos, ſecundum priora ſtatuta etiam ab uxoribus contine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Quod niſi fecerint, ab Eccleſiaſtico removeantur officio. Caeteros au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Clericos ad hoc non cogi, ſed ſecundum uniuſcujuſque Eccleſiae conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m obſervari debere.</hi> —Theſe were before the <hi>third</hi> General Council. —Add to theſe the <hi>fourth</hi> General Council of <hi>Chalcedon.</hi> Can. 13. —<hi>Quoniam in quibuſdam provinciis conceſſum eſt Pſalmiſtis &amp; Lectoribus,</hi> (ſe <hi>Apoſt. Can.</hi> 27. quoted before,) <hi>uxores ducere, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituit ſancta Synodus prorſus cuiquam ex his non licere alterius ſectae accipere uxorem,</hi> &amp;c. Where tis plain, that other Clergy beſides <hi>Pſalmiſts</hi> and <hi>Readers</hi> might not marry at all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>19</label> Hitherto I have kept within the times of the firſt four General Councils, to which we promiſe much conformity, I will joyn to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101527:12"/>theſe a Canon or two in <hi>Constantinopol. Conc. in Trullo,</hi> reckoned by the Eaſtern Church for a part of the <hi>ſixth</hi> General Council, tho it was not conſented to by the <hi>Roman</hi> Patriarch; Can. 6. —<hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam in Apoſtolicis Canonibus dictumeſt, cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m qui non duct ae uxore in Clerum promoventur, ſolum lectores &amp; cantores uxorem poſse ducere, &amp; nos hoc ſervantes decernimus, ut deinceps nulli penitus Hypodiacono, vel Diacono, vel Presbytero, poſt ſui Ordinationem, conjugium centra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here liceat.</hi> &amp;c. Canon. 12. <hi>Jubet omnino Antistites,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> Biſhops,) <hi>poſtquam ſunt ordinati, a propriis uxoribus ſecedere:</hi> and here they take notice of the 6th. <hi>Apoſtol.</hi> Canon, quoted before in the laſt §, and yet advance beyond it: <hi>quoniam Apoſtoli</hi> (ſay they) <hi>cum ſides inciperet, ad fidelium imbecillitatem ſe magis demittebant</hi> &amp;c. —Can. 13. —<hi>decernunt, Presbyteros a prioribus ſuis legitimis uxoribus non ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, ſed eo tempore quo ſacrificant; &amp; expellentes ſuas uxores pietatis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textu, excommunicandos.</hi> And this (ſay they) notwithſtanding the contrary cuſtom of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. Thus the Council in <hi>Trul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo.</hi> And ever ſince have the ſame laws and cuſtoms bin preſerved in the Eaſtern Churches, as we may ſee in the Anſwer of <hi>Jeremias</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in <hi>Epilogo</hi> to the Reformed, ſoliciting his approbation of their innovation in this matter, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring him of the Apoſtle's rule, <hi>Melius eſt nubere quam uri,</hi>— and his order, —<hi>Oportet Epiſcopum eſſe unius uxoris virum:</hi> to which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies this; —<hi>Proinde &amp; nos illis ſacerdotibus, qui in virginitate perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere non poſsunt, priuſquam tamen conſecrentur, &amp; Sacerdotes</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turi] <hi>ſiant</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ille autem</hi> [<hi>Sacerdos,</hi> entring into Orders, or others vowing Virginity] <hi>qui ſemel virginitatem profeſſus eſt, virgo perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neat, nec jam illi ullam amplius licentiam poſt votum ſuſceptum nubendi damus. Nemo enim mittens manum ad aratrum, &amp; reſpiciens retro, idoneus eſt conſequendo coeleſti regno.</hi> [Here is Prieſts, after their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, or others vowing Virginity; for ever after denied marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.] —This the modern law of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church; and if the prohibiting them afterward, makes them the more, who intend Prieſthood, to take wives before, and ſo many of the <hi>Greek</hi> Clergy <hi>de facto</hi> are married, to enjoy this liberty more than for neceſſity; yet this is an abuſe no ways countenanced by their Eccleſiaſtical Canons. Much leſs may we imagin that they are obliged by any ſuch law <hi>(ne periculo fornicandi ſe exponant)</hi> to take wives before they may enter into this Holy profeſſion, ſo contrary both to the Apoſtle's Counſel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. and the Church'es former Injunctions, when-as even all ſecular imployments have at leaſt the liberty of a ſingle life; and the Reformed themſelves, ſo great friends to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, yet impoſe no ſuch yoke upon their Clergy, nor hath any
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101527:13"/>that I know of entertained ſuch a fancy ſave <hi>Vigilantius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Out of the <hi>Canons</hi> then recited above you may obſerve, 1. That the Greek Church, who acknowledg and practiſe theſe <hi>Canons</hi> in this point to this day, allow indeed the uſe of their wives, except when they officiate, (but what if they officiate every day, as many Prieſts do?) to Prieſts married before Ordination, but not ſo to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; but permit not that any Ordained unmarried may after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward marry at all. <hi>2ly.</hi> Again, That thoſe married perſons, who were to be made Presbyters in the Roman Church, and Biſhops in the Oriental, might not ſeparate from their wives without conſent, received from the wives before ſuch Ordination or Conſecration of them. <hi>3ly.</hi> That ſuch continency was annexed to Holy Orders only by Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitution, and was rather <hi>Lex Continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> than <hi>Votum:</hi> which therefore hath bin capable of many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, and the <hi>Canons</hi> about it ſomewhat differing; and the Clergy more reſtrained by ſome of them than by others. But this ſeems to be a received ground amongſt them all in thoſe primitive times, that Continency is a general gift, at leaſt in <hi>potentia remota, i.e.</hi> which is by God denied to none uſing the means, and rightly preparing himſelf for it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Els how could they prudently make ſuch laws, ſtrictly prohibiting marriage for ſuch a number of men, involving alſo the Deacons, and Subdeacons, upon penalty of degradation from their office, (which laws you ſee, the Reformed, becauſe they hold continency a particular gift, only poſſible to ſome, generally decry.) How could they allow of a ſeparation (by conſent once given) of a man and his wife for ever, required, in the Roman Church, of all; in the Eaſtern, of Biſhops; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 Cor. 7.5? unleſs you will ſay, that the Church-Officers in time of Ordination could diſcern who had this gift, who not. Or, that there was no party coming to be ordained, or conſenting to ſuch a ſeparation, but was able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern it in himſelf, and that not only for the preſent, but always for the future; and likewiſe that none would preſent himſelf, that knew he had it not.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>20</label> Neither doth the Apoſtle's declaring from the Spirit, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that <hi>in the latter times there ſhould ariſe Apoſtates</hi> &amp;c, <hi>forbidding to marry, and commanding to abſtain from meats,</hi> any way prejudice theſe injunctions and practices of ancient Church, (nor conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of the latter times, herein following only her example.) 1. Becauſe the Apoſtle, by oppoſing to ſuch error, that <hi>every creature and ordinance of God is good,</hi> (according to <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31. and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101527:13"/>2.23, 24.) and therefore being <hi>ſanctified firſt, by the word of God and prayer,</hi> may lawfully be uſed, (ſee 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3, 4, 5.) ſheweth, that he means ſuch Apoſtates, as abſtain from, or prohibit, marriage and meats, as in themſelves unlawful, and unclean, and contami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating. Which thing can neither be objected to the ancient, nor modern Church-practice, uſing abſtinence from ſome meats for the chaſtiſement of the body, not for any uncleaneſs in the food; and not forbidding marriage to any ſingle perſon abſolutely, but only upon his voluntary undertaking ſuch an employment, with which they imagin a married condition not ſo well to ſute. In which caſe if neceſſary abſtinence from marriage be a fault, the Apoſtle himſelf may ſeem to comply with it in thoſe expreſſions of his 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.11.12. —<hi>2ly.</hi> Becauſe experience hath manifeſted the Apoſtle's prophecy to have bin moſt eminently fulfilled in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſons of theſe latter times, (whom theſe Fathers even in theſe points moſt vehemently reſiſted,) affirming downright all marriage, eſpecially with reference to procreation of children [therefore the married were adviſed by them, in ſuch manner to uſe their wives, as to avoid this, (ſee S. <hi>Auſt. de moribus. Manich.</hi> 18. <hi>c.</hi>)] to be unlawful, and the work or deſign of the Devil, as likewiſe fleſh-diet to be unclean and defiling. <hi>Animata abominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes interdicunt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Epiphanius haer.</hi> 47.) <hi>non continentioe gratia, ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> honeſtoe vitae, ſed ob timorem, &amp; imaginations ut non contaminentur ab animatorum eſu. Vino vero omnino non utuntur, Diabolicum eſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes.</hi> —And S. <hi>Auſtin contra Fauſt.</hi> 30. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c. Ipſam creaturam immundam dicitis, quod carnes Diabolus operetur faeoulentio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e materia, mali.</hi> —And <hi>de haereſ.</hi> 46. <hi>c. Non veſcuntur carnibus, tanquam de mortuis vel occiſis fugerit divina ſubſtantia. —Vinum non bibunt, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes, fel eſse principum tenebrarum.</hi> Such were ſome of the <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, Encratites, Montaniſts, Marcionites,</hi> and in the laſt place the <hi>Manichees,</hi> being as it were the laſt extract and quinteſſence of all thoſe former groſs errors, not a little potent even in S. <hi>Auſtin's</hi> times; who, not holding all things to have bin created by the ſame good God, but this lower world by an evil principle, or by the Prince of darkneſs, as they call him, affirm, in the begetting of a man, that the Soul, which they account to be a part of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of God himſelf, becomes fettered and impriſoned in the walls or handy-work of the devil, <hi>i.e.</hi> the body, from which it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain releaſed only by death; (therefore was marriage, occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch impriſonment, forborn by all their elect; and tho this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their auditors, yet (ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi>) it was, <hi>non dicences non eſſe peccatum, ſed peccantibus veniam largientes, propterea quod illis
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101527:14"/>neceſſaria miniſtrabant. con. Faust. Man.</hi> 30. <hi>l.</hi>) Likewiſe that the ſame part of God was continually more defiled, and encloſed by ſuch and ſuch groſs nouriſhments of the body. And when of ſuch errors they were accuſed by the Fathers, it was ordinary with them to recriminate the Orthodox with the ſame things; both for their frequent abſtinencies from fleſh, and ſome other fruits; and for their (to ſome perſons at leaſt) recommending virginity; who in this matter were anſwered by them after the ſame manner, as the Proteſtants, objecting the ſame things, are now by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> See concerning this the conteſt between <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the <hi>Manichee</hi> and S. <hi>Austin,</hi> (<hi>cont. Fauſt. Manich.</hi> 30. <hi>l.</hi>) and ſee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch Hereticks in the Church before the Manichees, <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus adv. Haereſ.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> there, of <hi>Saturninus</hi> and <hi>Baſilides,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Nubere autem &amp; generare, a Satana dicunt eſse. Multi autem ex iis &amp; ab animalibus abstinent</hi> &amp;c. —See <hi>Clem. Alexand. Strom.</hi> 3. near the beginning. <hi>Marcioniſtae quidem dicunt malam eſſe naturam ex mala materia</hi> &amp;c. —<hi>qua quidem ratione nolentes implere mundum, qui fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus eſt a Creatore, volunt abstinere a nuptiis, reſiſtentes ſuo Creatori</hi> &amp;c. —See much what the ſame relation with that of <hi>Irenaeus, in Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan. Haereſ.</hi> 23. and 46. and 47. <hi>Continentiam hic</hi> (i.e. <hi>Tatianus</hi>) <hi>praedicat, aſſerens nihil differre matrimonium a ſcortatione, ſed idem eſſe. Haer.</hi> 46. And the judgment of the Fathers commenting on this place of <hi>Timothy,</hi> applies it to the ſame men. See S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> or the Author of thoſe Comments in his works. <hi>Doctrina,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>quae nunc in Marcioniſtis, (quamvis pene defecerint,) vel Patricianis, aut maxime in Manichaeis denotatur. Hi enim &amp; Chriſtum natum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, &amp; nuptias prohibent, &amp; abstinendum a cibis tradunt.</hi> —Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom. <hi>de Manichaeis, &amp;. Encratiſtis, &amp; Marcioniſtis, omnique illorum officina hic loquitur</hi> &amp;c. —After whom ſee Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> on 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>note</hi> b. and the authorities there cited by him. And in the laſt place conſider what Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> himſelf (<hi>Apostacy of the latter times, p.</hi> 113.) granteth; namely, That errors about marriages and meats were no novelties in the Apoſtles own times, as the diligent Reader may eaſily collect out of their own Epiſtles: which makes it improbable, that he would ſpecifie the apoſtacy of latter times in theſe alone. Thus much Mr. <hi>Mede.</hi> Neither will that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion <hi>[in latter times]</hi> (the like expreſſions to which are found in many other places; ſee 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.—4.3. —2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3. —1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 2.18. —<hi>Jude</hi> 18. —2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.) carry the purpoſe of this prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy beyond the days of theſe ancient Herericks. For firſt, this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion doth not ſeem in the Apoſtle's drift ſo to indicate the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture times, as altogether to exclude the preſent; they reckoning
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101527:14"/>even their own times alſo a part of the <hi>laſt</hi> times, (ſee 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.17. 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 2.18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11.) and therefore, when they deſcribe ſuch wicked perſons, adviſing thoſe they writ to for the preſent to beware of them, to reſiſt them, to teach contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doctrine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.14. —4.2. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.2. 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.1. Or, <hi>2ly.</hi> if they do; yet thus, either we muſt free the Father's times from any ſuch imputation, as living before theſe latter times here propheſied of, (and conſequently in all future times we muſt abſolve all thoſe, who in theſe matters affirm no more than the Fathers did,) or, if theſe latter times involve the days of the Fathers alſo, (as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> fancies them to begin about 360, or 410, (<hi>Apoſtaſy p.</hi> 84.) yet in the ſame times we find alſo theſe hereticks contemporaries with, and much combated by, the Fathers. And therefore whether the prophecy (eying thoſe times) is likely to mean them, [i. e. <hi>the aſſerters of marriage and meats to be in themſelves utterly unlawful and unclean,</hi>] or to mean the Fathers rather, their Antagoniſts in theſe points, I leave to the Readers judgment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>21</label>
                     <hi>[5ly.]</hi> The ſame perſwaſion, in Antiquity, of the univerſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this gift to all ſeeking it, may be gathered from the vowing 1. of virginity, much uſed, allowed, recommended by them. Of which alſo we find ſomething in the ancient Councils. See <hi>Conc. Ancyran.</hi> before that of <hi>Nice,</hi> Can. 19. <hi>Quotquot virginitatem polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citam praevaricati ſunt, profeſſione contempta inter digamos haberi debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt.</hi> Here the practice thereof appears. —Conc. <hi>Elibertin.</hi> about the ſame time with that of the <hi>Nicene,</hi> Can. 13. <hi>Virgines quae ſe Deo dedicaverunt, ſi pactum perdiderint virginitatis, atque libidini ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vierint, non intelligentes quid amiſerint, placuit nec in fine dandam eis eſſe Communionem</hi> &amp;c. —Conc. <hi>Romanum</hi> at the ſame time under <hi>Silveſter,</hi> Can. 10. <hi>Nullus Epiſcoporum virginem ſacratam maritali conſortio</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> to receive the veil, and the ſolemnity of her marriage unto Chriſt) <hi>expetierit benedicere, niſi eam probaverit</hi> 72 <hi>annorum eſſe conſtitutam, ubi probabitur judicium verae pudicitiae, ut in</hi> 72 <hi>annis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirens Virum Chriſtum pudicitia cuſtodita, uncta vertice introducatur ad nuptias Chriſti, velamen capitis ferens, non cordis,</hi> (alluding, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to 2 Cor. 3.) This admiſſion was not, of her to vow at 72 years, who was <hi>ſacrata</hi> before, but of her, having ſo long faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully kept her vow, to ſuch an honour as this ceremony imports. In this ſame time, namely of the Emperor <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> were ſome former <hi>Roman</hi>-laws, prejudicial to Celibacy, abrogated by him for their ſakes, who had vowed to keep their virgin-chaſtity inviolate.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101527:15"/>
                     <hi>Euſeb. de vita Conſtant.</hi> 4. l. 26. c. —Concil. <hi>Carthaginenſe</hi> 3. Can. 33. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t virgines ſacrae, ſi privatae fuerint parentibus, a quibus cuſtodiebantur, providentia Epiſcopi, vel Presbyteri, ubi Epiſcopus abſens eſt, in Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterio virginum vel gravioribus foeminis commendentur, ut ſimul habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantes invicem ſe cuſtodiant, ne paſſim vagantes Eccleſiae laedant aeſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem.</hi> —And <hi>Carthag.</hi> 4. Can. 104. <hi>Si quae viduae quantumlibet ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huc in minoribus annis poſitae, &amp; matura aetate a viro relictae, ſe devove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt Domino, &amp; veſte Laicali abjecta, ſub teſtimonio Epiſcopi &amp; Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae religioſo habitu apparuerint, poſtea vero ad nuptias ſoeculares tranſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, ſecundum Apoſtolum, damnationem habebunt, quoniam fidem caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, quam Domino voverunt, irritam facere auſae ſunt. Tales ergo perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae ſine Chriſtianorum communione maneant,</hi> &amp;c. And afterward. <hi>De talibus ait Apoſtolus: Quum luxuriatae fuerint nubere volunt, haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes damnationem</hi> &amp;c. Theſe two Councils were before the fourth General Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> and both ſubſcribed by St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Laſtly, ſee <hi>Conc. Chalced.</hi> with which I will conclude; Can. 14. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aconiſſam non debere ante annos</hi> 40 <hi>ordinari ſtatuimus, &amp; hoc cum dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genti probatione, ſi vero—postea ſe nuptiis tradiderit, injuriam faciens gratioe Dei, haec Anathema ſit cum eo qui in nuptiis illius convenerit.</hi> —And Can. 15. <hi>Siqua virgo ſe dedicaverit Deo, ſimiliter Monachus, non licet eis nuptiis jungi. Si vero inventi fuerint hoc facientes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neant excommunicati.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>22</label> Again, in the Fathers nothing is more frequent, and that in the moſt ancient. S. <hi>Ignatius in Ep. ad Tharſenſes, &amp; ad Antiochenſes,</hi> making mention of <hi>Virgines Deo ſacrae</hi> in his time. In the firſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Viri diligite ſponſas veſtras,</hi> &amp;c. he ſaith, <hi>Eas, quae in virginitate, honorate ut ſacras Chriſti; eas, quae in honeſtate viduas, ut altare Dei,</hi> &amp;c. In the ſecond, —<hi>Populus ſubjiciatur Presbyteris &amp; Diaconis. Virgines cognoſcant, cui conſecraveruntſeipſas.</hi> This in the copies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by Archbiſhop <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hammond. Tertullian</hi> and S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> before A. D. 300, writ Tracts; one <hi>de velandis virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> (i.e. <hi>ſacris,</hi>) That they ſhould cover their faces with veils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where he mentions <hi>votum continentiae</hi> —<hi>viderit ipſum continentiae votum,</hi> p. 200. —and diſtinguiſheth between <hi>virgines hominum,</hi> and <hi>virgines Dei.</hi> —<hi>Ambiunt virgines hominum adverſus virgines Dei,</hi> &amp;c. p. 193. —and near the end he ſaith to ſuch <hi>Non mentiris nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam. Nupſiſti enim Chriſto; illi tradidiſti carnem tuam: illi ſponſasti maturitatem tuam,</hi> &amp;c. And of thoſe who ſhould offer to pull off this veil, he ſaith; <hi>O ſacrilegae manus, quae dicatum Deo habitum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahere potuerunt!</hi> &amp;c. —The other, <hi>de diſciplina &amp; habitu virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> (i.e. <hi>ſacrarum,</hi>) of whom he ſaith there: —<hi>Quae ſe Chriſto dica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verunt,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101527:15"/>&amp; a carnali concupiſcentia recedentes tam carne quam mente ſe Deo voverunt,</hi>— and that they were <hi>flos Eccleſiaſtici germinis</hi> &amp;c <hi>gaudere per illas, atque in illis largiter florere Eccleſiae matris glorioſam foecunditatem;</hi> and that thoſe of them who afterward yeild to luſt, are <hi>adulterae Chriſti.</hi> —And ſee his Epiſtle to <hi>Pomponius,</hi> about ſome that lived unchaſtly, after that <hi>exfide ſe Chriſto dicaverant, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati ſuaeſe destinarant, propter regna coeborum ſe caſtraverant,</hi> &amp;c. To theſe, that you may know that anciently alſo thoſe who lived Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtick lives made vows thereof, (the contrary of which ſome en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to perſwade us,) I wil add only two other teſtimonies: one out of S. <hi>Baſil, praeſat. conſtitut. Monaſt. Nuptias velut compedes fugit; vitam ſuam Deo conſecrat, &amp; castitatem profitetur, ut neque fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultas ipſi ſit converſionis ad nuptias:</hi> the other out of S. <hi>Auſtin, in Pſalm.</hi> 75. upon <hi>[Vovete &amp; reddite Domino Deo noſtro.]</hi> —<hi>Alii virginitatem ipſam ab ineunte aetate vovent</hi> &amp;c. <hi>iſti voverunt pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum.</hi> —<hi>Alius vovet relinquere omnia ſua diſtribuendo pauperibus, &amp; ire in communem vitam, in ſocietatem ſanctorum; magnum votum vovit.</hi> —<hi>Neſcio quae castimonialis nubere voluit. Aliquid mali voluit? mali plane. Quare? Quia jam vove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at Domino. Quid enim dixit de tali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Apoſtolus</hi> Paulus? (<hi>Cum dicat,</hi> viduas adoleſcentulas nubere ſi velint,) <hi>Quid autem ait de quibuſdam, quae voverunt, &amp; non reddide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt?</hi> habentes, <hi>inquit,</hi> damnationem, quia jam fidem irritam fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerunt. <hi>Nemo ergo poſitus in Monaſterio Frater dicat; Recedo de Monaſterio. Neque enim ſoli, qui ſunt in Monaſterio perventuri ſunt in regnum coelorum:</hi> —Reſpondetur ei; <hi>ſed illi non voverunt, tu vovisti.</hi> And concerning the married, by conſent vowing continency, and obligation afterward for ever to obſerve it, ſee S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s 199 Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to <hi>Ecdicia.</hi> The argument of which Epiſtle I will tranſcribe you. —<hi>Mulier quaedam</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> this <hi>Ecdicia</hi>] <hi>inſcio marito ſuſceperat vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Continentiae. Poſt tamen maritus aſſenſus eſt, &amp; continenter cum ea vixit, non ſinens tamen ut Monachae veſtem ſumeret. Tandem inſcio marito facultates omnes duobus</hi> [Monachis] <hi>veluti pauperibus erogavit, cum haberet filium puerum ex eodem viro. Maritus ſuſpicans eos Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachos eſſe ex eorum numero, qui penetrant &amp; praedantur domos alienas, reſiliit a propoſito, &amp; coepit maechari.</hi>— Now in this Epiſtle St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> blames <hi>Ecdicia</hi> indeed, for all the things above named, which ſhe had done without the conſent of her husband, commanding her to ſubmit, and ask his pardon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but as to the vow of Continency, to which they had once both conſented (notwithſtanding his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating,) he holds them both for ever obliged to it, and exhorts her, at leaſt, to perſeverance therein. —<hi>Quod enim</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Deo p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>riconſenſu ambo voveratis, perſeveranter uſque in finem redde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101527:16"/>ambo debuiſtis; a quo propoſito ſi lapſus eſt ille, tu ſaltem conſtantiſſime perſevera.</hi> Thus He. As for other quotations of Fathers, I refer you to the Controvertiſts: inſtead of which I will ſet you down the confeſſions concerning them of <hi>Calvin, Inſtit,</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 27. <hi>s.</hi> —<hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuta ſunt deinde tempora,</hi> (he means after the <hi>Conc. Nicen.</hi>) <hi>quibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuit nimis ſuperſtitioſa coelibatus admiratio,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Haec, quia videban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur reverentiam Socerdotio conciliare, magno plauſu etiam antiquitus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta eſſe fateor.</hi> Now the reaſon, why he cenſures not the times till after <hi>Nice,</hi> is the ſtory of <hi>Paphnutius,</hi> from which he gathers, thoſe former times <hi>Conjugium in Sacerdotio toleraſſe,</hi> not obſerving, or concealing, that it was only <hi>Conjugium</hi> contracted before Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Himſelf mean-while condemning the Canons which theſe times approved; <hi>quibus vetitum est, ne matrimonium contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent, qui perveniſſent ad ſacerdotii gradum.</hi> (Sect. 27. &amp; Sect. 29.28.) <hi>Nulla omnino conditione dandum eſſe locum iis Canonibus cenſeo, qui vinculum Coelibatus Eccleſiaſtico ordini injiciunt.</hi> Concerning vows of ſingle life, (13. c. 17. §.) <hi>Hoc, inquiunt, ab ultima memoria fuit obſervatum, ut ſe alligarent continentiae voto, qui totos ſe Domino dica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vellent.</hi> His Anſwer. <hi>Fateor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erre antiquitus quoque receptum fuiſse hum morem: ſed eam aetatem ſic ab omni vitio liberam fuiſſe non concedo, ut pro regula habendum ſit quicquid tunc factum eſt.</hi> —And the confeſſion of <hi>Pet. Martyr de Coelibatu &amp; Votis.</hi> —<hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quod verum eſt fateamur, cos in hac cauſa habemus iniquiores. Statim enim ab Apoſtolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum temporibus nimium tribui coeptum eſt Coelibatui.</hi> And of St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> he ſaith; <hi>Iſte vir Dei ſcribit</hi> (ſpeaking of Vows) <hi>ut homo decep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> Now the objections which are made, by the oppoſers of the law of Celibacy, for thoſe entring into Holy Orders; or of vows of Celibacy, for other perſons, out of the Canons of Councils, or the writings of the Fathers, are not againſt any thing here affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: but either, concerning ſome, who, having wives before Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, were not obliged afterward to abſtain from them, (allowed ſtill by the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, except to Biſhops only), *or concerning marriages contracted after Ordination or Vows, that ſuch are not <hi>irrita;</hi> of which opinion S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> is clearly, <hi>De bono Viduitatis,</hi> c. 8, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a thing granted by all after only ſimple vows; and after ſolemn, diſputed ſtill; whether ſuch perſons, who have ſo ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered, and made over themſelves in a particular eſpouſal to God, are made illegitimate for any Secular marriage afterward <hi>jure Divino,</hi> or only <hi>jure Eccleſiaſtico.</hi> (See <hi>Bell. de Monach.</hi> 2. l. 34. c. <hi>ſect. Reſpond: convenit.</hi> —) For the Church hath always claimed much power (as being not reſtrained by the Levitical law, <hi>qua talis,</hi> but only by that of Nature, nor preſcribed any thing by Chriſt) in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101527:16"/>ordering the matters of marriage; and in hindering ſome perſons from marrying, (even not to making the marriage <hi>illicitum</hi> to be done, but <hi>irritum</hi> when done,) who are not reſtrained there from by the Divine law, or the law of Nature. See if you pleaſe the diſcourſes of this in <hi>Eſtius</hi> 4. <hi>ſent.</hi> 40. <hi>d.</hi> 3. <hi>s.</hi> &amp;c. —28. <hi>d. ſect.</hi> 4, 8, 9. *or, concerning thoſe, who, after vowing continency, live in fornication and uncleanneſs, that ſuch, notwithſtanding their vow formerly made, had better marry than thus offend. Which is granted by all, after a ſimple vow: (hear what <hi>Bellarm.</hi> ſaith, (<hi>de Monach.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 34. c. ſect. <hi>Eſt autem.</hi>—) —<hi>Licet ſine peccato contrahi ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queunt, tamen verae nuptioe ſunt: &amp; ideo aliquo modo minus malum eſt nubere poſt votum ejuſmodi, quam aſſidue fornicari, tum ob ſidem conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gii, tum ob prolem legitimam, tum ob alia bona,</hi> &amp;c.) * But let it be granted them after a ſolemn alſo: but if from hence they would prove the lawfulneſs of marriage after vowing continency, the places they produce will no way bear it. They are three, much preſſed: one of S. <hi>Cyprian, Epiſtola ad Pomponium</hi> 62. <hi>Quod ſi ex fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſe Chriſto di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>averunt, pudice &amp; caſte ſine ulla fabula perſeverent; ita fortes &amp; ſtabiles praemium viginitatis expectent: ſi autem perſeverare nolunt, aut non poſſint, melius eſt ut nubant, quam in ignem delictis ſuis cadant.</hi> The ſecond of S. <hi>Hierom, Ep. ad Demetriadem</hi> 8. <hi>Sanctum Virginum propoſitum &amp; coeleſtis Angelorumque familiae gloriam quarun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam non bene ſe agentium nomen infamat; quibus aperte dicendum eſt, ut aut nubant, ſi ſe non poſſint continere; aut contineant, ſi nolunt nube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi> The third of S. <hi>Auſtin, de ſancta Virginitate,</hi> 34. c. upon that of the Apoſtles, 1 Tim. 5. <hi>Nubere volunt.</hi> —<hi>Hae igitur</hi> (he ſpeaks of thoſe who have vowed chaſtity) <hi>quae nubere volunt, &amp; ideo non nubunt, quia impune non poſſunt, (quae melius nuberent, quam urerentur) quas poenitet profeſſionis, &amp; piget confeſſionis, niſi correctum cor diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, &amp; Dei timore rurſus libidinem vincant, in mortuis deputandae ſunt.</hi> &amp;c. 1 Tim. 5.6. —But in theſe places the Fathers, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of two evils, if one of them they will do, wiſh rather the leſs to be done; and prefer marriage, being in it ſelf, tho not to them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a vow, lawful, before living in fornication, and other unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, neither to them after vows, nor before in it ſelf, lawful: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſay, <hi>ſi nolunt continere,</hi> or <hi>perſeverare, nubant.</hi> Which mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage yet none at all allow lawful; namely to none who can keep their vows. As for the <hi>non poſſunt,</hi> they ſpeak if not of them as no way able to keep their vow, (for then indeed I grant, marriage would be lawful, if the vow of virginity were impoſſible to be kept,) but of them as, by their own fault (which they may redreſs [therefore S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>niſi correctum cor dirigant,</hi> &amp;c,])
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101527:17"/>impotent. Which may clearly appear (to any who delight not rather to make the Fathers to contradict themſelves, even where their ſpeeches are moſt eaſily reconciled) both by the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers allowing theſe perpetual vows, and their holding in all the poſſibility of continency; ſhewed before. Of which alſo hear S. <hi>Hierom,</hi> (<hi>comment. in Matt.</hi> 19. c.) upon <hi>[Non omnes capiunt.] Nemo putet ſub hoc verbo vel fatum vel fortunam introduci: quod hi ſunt virgines, quibus a Deo datum ſit, aut quos quidam caſus ad hoc ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duxerit: ſed his datum eſt, qui petierunt, qui voluerunt; qui ut accipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent laboraverunt. Omni enim petenti dabitur, &amp; pulſanti aperietur,</hi> &amp;c. —<hi>Qui poteſt capere, capiat; qui poteſt pugnare, pugnet; ſuperet, ac triumphet.</hi> —And <hi>adverſus</hi> Jovinianum 2. l. 19. c. to this Apoſtate Monk, who equalled a virginal and conjugal ſtate, he ſaith: <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines tuoe, quas prudentiſſimo conſilio quod nemo unquam legerat nec au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dierat, de Apoſtolo docuiſti</hi> [melius eſt nubere, quam uri] <hi>occultos ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulteros in apertos verterunt maritos. Non ſuaſit hoc Apoſtolus, non electionis vas;</hi> Virgilianum <hi>eonſilium eſt,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Conjugium vocat, hoc praetexit nomine culp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m:</p>
                  <p>See S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> (<hi>Confeſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi>) —<hi>Putabam me miſerum fore nimis, ſi foeminae privarer amplexibus: &amp; medicinam miſericordiae tuoe ad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andem infirmitatem ſanandam non cogitabam, quia expertus non eram: &amp; propriarum virium credebam eſse continentiam, quarum mihi non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram conſcius; cum tam ſtultus eſſem, ut neſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>irem, ſicut ſcriptum eſt,</hi> (Wiſdom, <hi>ſeu Sapient.</hi> 8. c. 21.) Neminem eſſe poſſe continentem, niſi tu dederis. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tique dares, ſi gemitu interno pulſarem aures tuas, &amp; fide ſolida in te jactarem curam meam.</hi> —(<hi>De adulterinis Conjugiis</hi> 2. l. 20. c.) <hi>Solemus eis</hi> [qui propter adulterium dimiſſis conjugibus ſuis, alias volunt ducere, &amp; quum prohibentur, infirmitatem nobis car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis opponunt] <hi>proponere etiam continentiam Clericorum; qui plerum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad eandem ſarcinam ſubeundam capiuntur inviti, eamque ſuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eptam uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad debitum finem, Domino adjuvante, perducunt. Dicimus ergo eis; Quid ſi &amp; vos ad hoc ſubeundum populorum violentia caperemini, nonne ſuſceptum caſte</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> in celibacy) <hi>cuſtodiretis officium, repente converſi ad impetrandas vires a Domino, de quibus nunquam antea cogitaſtis?</hi> See the like in Pſalm. 137. <hi>Nemo praeſumat viribus ſuis reddere quod voverit: Qui te hortatur, ut voveas; ipſe adjuvat, ut reddas.</hi> So o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fathers alſo. <hi>Chryſoſt. Comment. in Matt.</hi> 19. His datum eſt qui ſponte id eligunt: <hi>Quod ideo dixit, ut oſtenderet, ſuperiore nobis auxilio opus eſſe; quod quidem omnibus paratum eſt, ſi volumus in hae lucta evadere ſuperiores.</hi> Add to this that place of S. <hi>Auſtin in Pſal.</hi> 75. quoted before §. 22. and that 104. Can. of <hi>Conc. Carthag.</hi> 4. ſubſcribed by him, quoted before §. 21. with ſome others there
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101527:17"/>to the ſame purpoſe, where they deny marriage lawful to Votaries, and Anathematize them. To which I will add that of S. <hi>Ambroſe ad Virginem lapſam,</hi> 5. c. <hi>Quae ſe ſpopondit Chriſto, &amp; ſacrum velamen accepit, jam nupſit; jam immortali juncta eſt vivo, &amp; jam ſi voluerit nubere communi lege conjugii adulterium perpetrat.</hi> —And that of S. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> ſpoken by way of caution to young <hi>Theodorus</hi> deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Monaſtick life. <hi>Paraen.</hi> 2. —<hi>Honorabile,</hi> inquit, <hi>connubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; cubile immaculatum. Sed tibi jam non eſt integrum jura connu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bii ſervare; coelesti enim ſponſo ſemel junctum illum relinquere, &amp; uxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris laqueis implicari, adulterii crimen incurrere eſt. Quamvis millies hoc ipſum nuptias voces, ego tamen &amp; adulterio</hi> (that is, the adultery of another man who hath not vowed, not his, as I conceive him) <hi>illud tanto pejus affirmo, quanta major ac melior mortalibus Deus. Nunc autem nihil in te penitus tui juris eſt.</hi> —<hi>Nam ſi mulier proprii corporis non habet potestatem, ſed vir: multo magis hi, qui Chriſto potius, quam ſibi vivunt, ditionem corporis ſui habere non poſſunt.</hi> So S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who holds not the marriages of Votaries to be null, or no true marria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, (ſee <hi>de bono Vidutiatis,</hi> c. 8, 9, 10, 11.) yet ſaith in the ſame place, c. 11. <hi>Non poſſum quidem dicere foeminas a propoſito meliore lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas ſi nupſerint adulteria eſſe, non conjugia: ſed plane non dubitaverim dicere lapſus &amp; ruinas a caſtitate ſanctiore, quae vovetur Deo, adulteriis eſſe pejores. Si enim ad offenſionem Chriſti pertinet, cum membrum ejus fidem non ſervat marito, quanto gravius offenditur, cum illi ipſi non ſervatur fides in eo, quod oblatum exigit, qui non exegerat offerendum?</hi> This in anſwer to thoſe places, wherein tis pretended, the Fathers held marriage lawful after vows; or continency to ſeem not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But the Apoſtle ſufficiently decides this buſineſs (at leaſt as the Fathers underſtood him) in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. who affirms his young votaries to have <hi>damnation,</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> great guilt upon them,) for break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their former faith or vow by marrying. Now this denying of marriage, the remedy of incontinency, to all ſuch as have paſſed a vow, argues that the Fathers held the gift of continency denied to none ſuch. Which if it be true, the only conſiderable objection (that I know of) againſt a Monaſtick life is here alſo removed. For as concerning the other two vows, * That (commonly called) of <hi>Poverty,</hi> provided, that one remain ſtill either poſſeſſed of what in humane probability is enough to ſupply him with neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or have a trade or a profeſſion (amongſt which I reckon preaching of the Goſpel one) wherewith from time to time to get his living, (for the <hi>labourer is worthy of his hire,</hi> as our Saviour told his diſciples, when he ſent them abroad to preach without any proviſion), and may in reaſon preſume he ſhall receive it; and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101527:18"/>*That of <hi>Obedience,</hi> provided, it be engaged only for things law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, about which lawfulneſs, when any doubt happens, he is to be guided by the Church'es, not his private Superiors judgment: (Which I think, in no Monaſtical inſtitution that ever was, can be ſhewed to be peremptorily denied to any, for the ordinary plea of many of the Roman Doctors is contrary; namely, that no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority leſs than infallible (which Superiors are not) can oblige to abſolute obedience and ſubmiſſion to their judgment in matters credible or practicable in order to our ſalvation (See <hi>Notes of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly;)</hi> Tho thoſe who are under Authority are prudentially ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed, rather to ſubmit in all things to their Superiors (moſt likely) better judgments, than (with very little ſign of humility) indulge their own; and cauſleſly afflict their Society with appeals and conteſts:) Theſe two vows, I ſay, thus qualified, are not liable to any juſt exceptions. And indeed the former we ſee done frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amongſt us, in many parting for ever with their eſtates (only what is neceſſary reſerved) to their Son: why not then to the poor? and the latter in Servants promiſing, of alſo ſwearing obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their Matters; why not to a Spirtual Superior?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>23</label> Neither is there (beſides the examples we have of this vowing both in Scriptures and the Fathers) as ſeems to me any argument to be drawn from reaſon, why we may not preſume on God's aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and enablement of us, to perform ſuch vow; either becauſe it is vowing of a thing not abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation; or becauſe we are not certain of our ability, and command of our will, to uſe the means, which ability alſo we have not from our ſelves, but from God. For 1. are not moſt of our vows (yet theſe grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed lawful) about things, which, as ſome way advantageous, yet, are not abſolutely neceſſary to our ſalvation? as the vowing, * of abſtinence from the further uſe of ſome ſenſual, tho lawful plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, formerly to us an occaſion of ſin; * of giving ſuch a propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of alms (ſuppoſe half of our eſtates) to the poor, (ſuch a one was <hi>Ananias</hi> his vow, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. whoſe fault, ſo much aggravated by S. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſeems to be more in his keeping back part, after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voting it to God, than in pretending, by a lye, to bring it all: ſee the inference ver. 3. <hi>But Peter</hi> &amp;c.) * of uſing every day two or three times of prayer extraordinary; * of not drinking wine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of many former temptations by it to exceſs. And <hi>2ly,</hi> is not the performance of all theſe only by the power God gives us, (who cannot think a good thought, much leſs curb the leaſt appetite, without him,) and therefore we give him thanks alſo for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101527:18"/>of them? 3. And again, make we not in baptiſm a vow of things neceſſary to ſalvation, <hi>i.e.</hi> of <hi>repentance,</hi> and of <hi>faith?</hi> but the expreſſions concerning which in Scripture are the ſame as thoſe concerning continency. to wit, that they <hi>are not given to all:</hi> [See <hi>Jo.</hi> 6.37, 39, 64, 65. —2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. —<hi>Matt.</hi> 13.11. <hi>It is given unto you to know the mysteries of the kingdom of heaven, but to them it is not given.</hi>] Not as if God abſolutely denied ſuch a gift to them, but only upon their non-preparation, and other obſtacles, which by their own fault hindred them from receiving it; for ſo our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour expounds himſelf in the next words, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>For whoſoever hath, to him ſhall be given.</hi> In the ſame manner may it be ſaid of continency; <hi>non omnibus datur;</hi> but <hi>habenti</hi> (i.e. to men uſing thoſe endeavors and preparations towards it, which God hath given them power to uſe) <hi>dabitur.</hi> (<hi>Jo.</hi> 12.39.—<hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. compared 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48. (For which expreſſions if we make the vow of continency unlawful, why not the other? Now who is there that may not lawfully vow, to repent of his ſins, to believe in God to his lives end, to obſerve God's commands, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> (118. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 106.108. <hi>v.</hi>) yet as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nemo praeſumat viribus ſuis red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere quod voverit. Qui te hortatur ut voveas, ipſe adjuvat ut reddas.</hi> [In Pſalm. 137.] Here it is ſaid; there is not the ſame reaſon: becauſe Faith is a thing neceſſary to ſalvation, not ſo Virginal Continency, therefore we cannot juſtly have the ſame confidence, that God, ſurely not wanting to us in neceſſaries, muſt needs ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply us alſo in ſuperfluities. <hi>Reſp.</hi> Doubtleſs, ſince God, as he hath commanded duty, ſo alſo hath adviſed perfection, as not in the one, ſo neither in the other, is he wanting in his gift, to thoſe that ſeek it; eſpecially the latter undertaking (as higher) deſerving more encouragement. Elſe why is not <hi>[petenti dabitur]</hi> reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo to neceſſaries? and why may a man lawfully make vows in other things, that he conceives profitable, but acknowledgeth are not abſolutely neceſſary to his ſalvation, (as in the things men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before, as alſo in other rules of perfection, 1 Cor. 9. Luk. 12.33. Matt. 19.29.) if he may not preſume on God's aſſiſtance in ſuch things only profitable, without which he is able of himſelf to do nothing profitable. 4. Again, I know not why, if we may ſafely vow the keeping of any of God's commandements, and may make a <hi>covenant with our eyes, not to look upon a woman to luſt after her,</hi> why, I ſay, we may not alſo, to guard our paſſion from being ſet on fire, and from burning; ſince the former ſeems to be the more difficult.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:101527:19"/>
                  <p n="5">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>24</label> 5. To which this further may be added: That Continency, as any other thing advantaging us in God's Service, from Vows receives a much higher value, which may invite us to ſuch pious engagements) than without it; whilſt it proceeds from an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction more confirmed and ſtedfaſt in good. A reſolute vow having the virtue of an habit; and to act good, as it were neceſſarily, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Angelical: and he that vows offering up and ſacrificing to God, not the act only of continency with others for the preſent; but the power or faculty thereof for ever; and the fruit, together with the tree that bears it. Therefore find we frequent exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and examples of vowing in Scripture: ſee <hi>Pſ.</hi> 76.11. <hi>Jon.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 19.21. &amp;c. And very expedient doubtleſs it is (after ſome trial and experience of our having a reaſonable command over our ſelves, and of our not ſuffering a very tyrannical maſtery of our paſſions) to paſs a vow in ſuch matters to fortify our ſelves againſt temptations, and the mutability of our inclinations; by which the leſs former tye we have of our ſelves, the eaſilier we are ſeduced. <hi>Faelix neceſſitas, quae ad melior a compellit,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> of Vows.</p>
                  <p>As for thoſe places of the Apoſtle which are urged, againſt vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, at leaſt before <hi>ſixty,</hi> or for leave given to marry, tho it be after vows, upon incontnency; [as 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Let not a widow be taken into the number under</hi> 60 <hi>years old:</hi> —and 14. <hi>I will therefore, that the younger women marry</hi> &amp;c. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9. <hi>If they cannot contain let them marry:</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 35. <hi>I ſpeak not that I may cast a ſnare upon you.</hi>] In anſwer to them, I take this firſt for granted; that all thoſe (young or old) who have the power to be continent, may ſafely vow it; ſince the reaſon given by the Reformed, why it may not be vowed, is, becauſe it is a thing not in our power. Again, I ſay, that if theſe places prove, either that continency before 60. may not be vowed, or marrying after a vow may be lawful, upon this reaſon, becauſe ſome perſons before <hi>ſixty,</hi> and after vowing, cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; then the Apoſtle will be made to contradict himſelf. For according to this he could not ſay of the Juniors, (whoſe particular gift of continency he could not know, but had rather reaſon to preſume, from the miſcarriage he ſaw in them, that they had it not,) that <hi>they had damnation,</hi> for marrying; or for not keeping their vow or promiſe to Chriſt, which they could not keep; but <hi>damnation,</hi> for making ſuch a vow, which they muſt neceſſarily break. For, <hi>Non eſt peccatum violare, quod ſervare impoſſibile est;</hi> and it was as lawful to break ſuch a vow, as unlawful to make it. But yet notwithſtanding this, the Apoſtle plainly ſaith, damnation they had for marrying, and for breaking this promiſe, not for mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101527:19"/>it. I conclude therefore, that the Apoſtle's advice here of marriage is not * to Votaries, nor abſolutely to all other younger women: for ſo his <hi>volo juniores nubere</hi> here would be contrary to his <hi>volo omnes eſſe ſicut meipſum,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.7. and would lay an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation on all young folks to marry: But * to thoſe that are in ſuch a manner qualified, as thoſe were that miſcarried: <hi>ſo qualified;</hi> not from want of power from God to contain, but want of will, and of a ſtedfaſt purpoſe to make uſe of that power, (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes it 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.37.) which inſtability of the will, and pronenes to incontinency (that is in ſome much more than in others) eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ought well to examin before they vow; that ſo they may make uſe of the lawful remedy, which in the ſecond place God hath provided for it, namely marriage; if they do not aſpire to the higher cure thereof by prayer, and mortifications. See Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> in his Paraphraſe, expounding it thus, <hi>[That thoſe who have not attained to ſuch gravity of mind, and command over themſelves, do, in that caſe, betake themſelves to a married life:]</hi> —So, in that text, <hi>[if they cannot contain, let them marry.]</hi> (Where note, that our Tranſlation renders, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, If they <hi>cannot</hi> contain; and ſo <hi>Matt.</hi> 19.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, All men <hi>cannot</hi> receive this ſaying <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without rule or precedent, that I know of: for the <hi>Vulgar</hi> hath it, <hi>omnes non capiunt: &amp; ſi non ſe continent.</hi>) The advice is not, to any that have an obligation to contain, (tho actually perchance they do not ſo), as it is not to the married; tho one party be ſick, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or impotent; nor to thoſe who have vowed, it being proved, that ſuch may contain, from the Apoſtle's ſaying, <hi>they have dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in marrying;</hi> who yet actually <hi>non ſe continebant:</hi> But the advice is to thoſe only, that are free from any obligation againſt marriage; that if they perceive themſelves ſo affected, as that they have much temptation, and no ſtedfaſt purpoſe to contain, if they have gotten (which yet is by their own defect) ſo little pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and maſtery over their will, (which maſtery is acquired by ſome pains and practice) as that they cannot (not cannot <hi>poſſibly</hi> but cannot <hi>without much difficulty</hi>) contain, (for we ſay we cannot do a thing, tho in our power, which we can hardly do): that then they ſhould make uſe of the common remedy allowed by God for it. All which weakneſſes, ſince they are by induſtry remediable, excuſe none from continency, who have already made any engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to it. To the 3d. place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.35. I grant a vow raſhly undertaken to be a dangerous ſnare: <hi>raſhly,</hi> I ſay, <hi>i.e.</hi> without well proving before it what maſtery we have over our carnal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations. Laſtly, for the admiſſion of none under <hi>ſixty,</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:101527:20"/>the Apoſtle ſeems to preſcribe this age with reſpect to their impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency then to get their living, and liableneſs to want, (ſee <hi>ver.</hi> 4, and 16.) and to their ſtaydneſs and gravity, [ſee <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14.] as much or more than to their continency, in which a leſſer age would have rendred them ſecure. But ſuppoſe the Apoſtle chiefly to have reference to this, yet was it not done as if any leſſer age hath not a power of continency; or experiencing their ability to live ſingle, might not alſo reſolve it: but becauſe the Church had not the ſame means to be aſſured of their inclinations, and was much concerned in her firſt growth, after the experience too of ſome miſcarriages, thus to prevent all ſcandal. But later Church, upon experience of the chaſt behaviour of ſuch perſons from the power of more diſcipline, due reſtraint, <hi>amp;c.</hi> thought not her ſelf obliged by this rule fitted for the Apoſtles days. But as S. <hi>Paul,</hi> from the lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of younger women, admitted them at 60: ſo the 4th. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> Can. 14. <hi>cum diligenti probatione</hi> admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them at <hi>forty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <p n="10">X. As God hath encouraged us to ſingle life by recommending it; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>25</label>
                  <note place="margin">Yet it more difficult, than the matter of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Vow.</note> and denies the power to none at all, taking the pains, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the means, that are neceſſary to procure it; So I grant, that the <hi>act and exerciſe of Continency,</hi> and purity, <hi>is much more difficultly attained,</hi> than any other matter of a <hi>Vow whatever;</hi> and the ſin, which the undiſcreet attempters thereof fall into, if they miſcarry, very abominable. Therefore is there nothing in all the Scripture recommended with ſo much caution, and putting men in mind of their own abilities, as this: which appears both in our Saviour's limitations, <hi>Matt.</hi> 19.11, 12. and in the Apoſtle's proceeding ſo tenderly in this point, and with ſuch cautious and ſuſpended ſteps, (ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2, 6, 7, 25, 28, 35, 36.) tho much commending it, yet warily recommending it: looking doubtles as onone ſide at the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly perfection of this virtue, ſo on the other at the hainouſnes and filthines of thoſe crimes, and the great peril of thoſe ſnares, that men, avoiding, and obſtinate againſt, the common merciful remedy of marriage, were endangered to fall into, in an unmodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied purſuit of this grace. More <hi>difficultly,</hi> I ſay, <hi>is this grace at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained,</hi> both by reaſon of this ſtrong impreſſion made in our nature by the moſt wiſe providence, for the neceſſary uſe of propagation; and by reaſon of the concupiſcence of the fleſh; which, as it was the firſt exorbitancy appearing in <hi>Adam,</hi> (<hi>They ſaw that they were naked,</hi> Gen. 3.7. being only a modeſt expreſſion of the riſing of concupiſcence; compared with <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.25. therefore followed by ſhame); ſo retains it its ſtrength in all his ſons, beyond any other
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101527:20"/>paſſion whatſoever: to which likewiſe one perſon (and in him one age of his life) may have yet a far greater pronity than another, by the greater heat of their conſtitution; natural impetuoſity of their paſſion; more liberal diet; much reſt and vacancy from imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; converſation amongſt tempting objects, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that ſuch, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out extream difficulty, cannot contain, as it alſo many times hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens even to them after divorce, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> (who, all grant, have from God the power of containing, if they will uſe their beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors). And in reſpect of the great ſtrength of the temtations of luſt, beyond all other, and of theſe great impediments in ſome, more than in others, (<hi>i.e.</hi> the natural temper, age, condition of life, former habits, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> and of moſt mens averſeneſs to undergo thoſe rigors and mortifications, which procure and preſerve continency, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>) I conceive it is; that our Saviour anſwered his forward diſciples voting, upon his diſcours, that none ſhould marry; * that to <hi>all this was not given,</hi> and that <hi>ſome only could receive it;</hi> and ſo the Apoſtle by the ſame ſpirit, * <hi>that every one hath his proper gift of God,</hi> one after this manner, and another after that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.7. and * that there was a neceſſity to ſome parents of <hi>giving their virgin in marriage,</hi> (ver. 36, 37.) therefore he ſaith, <hi>it is not given to all,</hi> i. e. without ſuch pains-taking as ſome other gifts are; <hi>Nor do all receive it:</hi>] For tho power to contain is given to any who uſe the means, ſubdue their paſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet few there are, who can without much difficulty and reſolution ſo maſter their will, ſubdue their paſſions; few, who have a temper naturally ſo calm, or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially ſo rebated, that they can arrive to ſuch a power. And ſo, <hi>every one hath his proper gift of God,</hi> &amp;c.] <hi>i. e.</hi> Firſt, in reſpect of gifts of nature; men are of ſeveral tempers and abilities, ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined more to one paſſion, as enamour'dnes, ſome to another, <hi>[as continency,]</hi> ſome more, ſome leſs, ſubject to be tempted; ſome fitted for one ſort of life, ſome another; which all yet are the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributions of God, (ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.17.) So that ſome can more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſome not without almoſt inſuperable difficulty, contain; for we ſay, we <hi>cannot</hi> do, tho a thing in our power, what we can <hi>hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do,</hi> or which is very troubleſome to us to effect. See <hi>Luke</hi> 14.20. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.3. —Such phraſes are not unfrequent in Scripture, <hi>Jo.</hi> 13.36. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> to 34. <hi>Jo.</hi> 6.65. ſpoken in things, of which we do not deny an abſolute poſſibility, whilſt by prayer <hi>&amp;c</hi> may be attained ſtronger inclinations; but yet in them we ſuppoſe to ſome a preſent impotency, and impromptitude of their will, and waywardneſs of their inclinations; eſpecially where the thing requires a ſtrong <hi>conatus,</hi> and a ſtout ſpirit, as <hi>Peter's dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101527:21"/>for Chriſt; their forſaking friends, and all they had, for Chriſt.</hi> Luk. 14.26. and 33. <hi>Their believing in Christ,</hi> eſpecially at that time, when appearing to them in ſuch weakneſs of our fleſh; none of theſe things (tho) being abſolutely impoſſible to them. <hi>2ly,</hi> in reſpect of gifts of grace <hi>every man hath his proper gift of God;</hi> ſome, ſuperior; ſome, inferior, graces; ſome, Virginal, ſome only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal, chaſtity, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9.) according to every man's capacity, (<hi>Matt.</hi> 25.15.) or endeavours: which not premiſed, the grace is not beſtowed. For we muſt know, that God always gives not his habitual graces at firſt, but excites and aſſiſts our endeavors for them; and afterwards crowns theſe endeavors with them. And hence, becauſe moſt do not well imploy God's former grace, (in which he is not wanting to thoſe, whom he queſtions for want of the latter) the other happen to be given but to a very few. Sec <hi>Matt.</hi> 13, 11. concerning that neceſſary grace of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual illumination, <hi>[To you it is given; to them it is not given;]</hi> and <hi>Jo.</hi> 12.39. concerning faith; <hi>[Therefore they could not believe.]</hi> See §. and ſo <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.5. concerning the favors of God, that he is ready to do for us, but we are uncapable of receiving; <hi>[And he could there do no mighty work.]</hi> In all which the deficiency is not to be underſtood to proceed from the want of will in God to give, but from the want of preparation in them to receive. (See <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.11. compared with 12. —<hi>Mar.</hi> 6.5. compared with 6.) If they receive not, becauſe God gives not; <hi>Matt.</hi> 19.11. and if God gives not, becauſe they do not by prayer, and other means, prepare themſelves for it; it follows, the prime reaſon, why they receive not, is becauſe they are unmortified, or unprepared. Now the exhortation <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>He that is able to receive it, let him</hi> &amp;c. See <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.22. plainly ſuppoſeth, * that God gives it to thoſe that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and the inſtance in ſome that <hi>make themſelves Eunuchs,</hi> prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, * that men alſo make themſelves able; <hi>able,</hi> by God's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, and preventing and aſſiſting aid, or grace, from whom is all ability. Which ability alſo ſuppoſes that he gives to ſome, not others, only in the ſame ſenſe as he gives faith, and other graces; (ſee <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. compared with 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.2.) yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as all may both pray for faith, and upon their endeavor preſume they ſhall receive it; and may promiſe and vow unto God to be faithful; ſo notwithſtanding the former expreſſions (if no other reaſon be alledged) we may ſay the ſame of Continency; That it is a gift <hi>attainable by all,</hi> as it is a gift <hi>by few attained.</hi> Thus much concerning the grace. But <hi>3ly,</hi> in reſpect of the faculty it ſelf, and the uſing of it well, in our endeavors to attain ſuch a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101527:21"/>grace, tis true alſo, that our being willing to do a thing is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently called God's gift; and there is nothing, of which we can ſay, tis our fault or infirmity that we do it not, but that we may as truly ſay, it is God's gift, if we do it. (See <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.23. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.1. <hi>Ex.</hi> 4.11. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.31. —10.15. —<hi>Ezr.</hi> 6.22. <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.11.) Therefore alſo this our deſiring ſuch a grace to be given us, or our entertaining ſuch a grace offered us, is alſo in ſome ſenſe another gift or grace of God to us, without which we ſhould not have poſſeſſed his other grace; and ſo, our own endeavour, as well as the grace we ſeek for, is all gift and grace, tho we ſhould go <hi>in infinitum;</hi> till we alſo find (as the moſt ordinary do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the School is) that the firſt motion of the will to embrace God's grace is alſo the grace, gift, or work of God in us: els if this motion of the will were from it ſelf, in any ſenſe contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct to that of being from God, then there would be ſome good in us, not from God; then ſomething, which we had not received; and ſo, place for merit, and boaſting; contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.2, 4. —3.17. But I conceive, tis not ſaid of theſe firſt gifts of God, (<hi>i.e.</hi> of his firſt excitings of the will; his both preventing and aſſiſting aids and helps of the will, in its uſing the means to attain his fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and richer, habitual, and inherent graces,) that <hi>non omnibus data ſunt;</hi> but of thoſe other ſecond graces, which are given but to few, becauſe the means, and his former commoner aids are uſed by few: of which it is ſaid, that, only <hi>to him that hath, ſhall be given.</hi> Of thoſe firſt aids therefore we may ſafely ſay, that they are ſo far common to all, (to whom is come the ſound of the Goſpel, and who ſhall be judged at the laſt day by the Goſpel) that it is their fault, in any duties, which are abſolutely command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, and their defect, in any counſels of perfection, if they, by not making uſe of them, come ſhort of ſuch duty or perfection; and, that any thing being thus ſaid to be God's gift hinders not, but that it likewiſe may be ſaid alſo to be in man's power, (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a power, in man, but, from God,) as long as the tender of ſuch a gift is made to him, and ability alſo to acquire it given to him. But of this more in my <hi>Notes of Grace.</hi> Yet ſince, there are ſome that allow not the means to attain faith, or other duties command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, common to all to whom the Goſpel is preached, (therefore <hi>P. Martyr,</hi> 3. <hi>claſſ.</hi> 7. <hi>c. Commun. locorum.</hi> argues thus: <hi>Magis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deretur debere commune eſſe omnibus hominibus donum eſſicacis vocatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ad ſidem in Chriſtum, quam donum ad Coelibatum.</hi> —<hi>Sed inter illos qui eandem praedicationem audiunt, non omnes a Deo trahuntur.</hi> Where he quotes Jo. 6.44. <hi>Nemo venit ad me:</hi>) Let but ſo much be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101527:22"/>granted from them, of the means to attain continency, as is, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain faith; and this will ſerve our turn, without reaſoning the point any further in this place; for then ſee what will follow §. 23. In granting therefore, that the uſing of the means alſo to obtain graces from God is the gift of God; yet we affirm, that it is only by their own default (for which ſee <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.57. <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.21. <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.34. <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.37. <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.4. —8.10.) if in things abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely commanded, and their own defect, if in things recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their greater perfection, that ſuch do not uſe the means, and that they may uſe them if they will. Becauſe theſe muſt conſiſt together, <hi>i.e.</hi> * that <hi>we can do no good</hi> (ſmall or great) <hi>but from God;</hi> and * that <hi>we have free-will to do good,</hi> and if we do not good, tis by our own default; and * that when we do any good, tis not without our own endeavour. Els we ſhould be free from ſin in not obſerving the divine exhortations; and there would be no vice, nor virtue; and conſequently no (juſt) puniſhment, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. See concerning this S. <hi>Auſtin, De Gratia &amp; libero Arbitrio</hi> 4. <hi>cap. Nunquid non liberum arbitrium</hi> Timothei <hi>eſt exhortatus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolus, dicens,</hi> Contine teipſum? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.23. —<hi>Et in hac re po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testatem voluntatis oſtendit, ubi ait,</hi> Non habens neceſſitatem; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatem autem habens ſuae voluntatis, ut ſervet virginem ſuam. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.37. <hi>Et tamen non omnes capiunt verbum hoc, ſed quibus da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt,</hi> &amp;c. —<hi>Itaque ut hoc verbum, quod non ab omnibus capitur, ab aliquibus capiatur, &amp; Dei donum eſt, &amp; liberum arbitrium</hi> &amp;c. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will this be ſufficient to hinder a vow, becauſe it is only of God's gift (that we are willing to uſe the means) to keep and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil it. For alſo we cannot do any thing he commands, unles he gives us the will; and yet may we vow to do any thing he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <p n="11">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>26</label>
                  <note place="margin">Therefore not haſtily to be vowed.</note>XI. And in reſpect of theſe conſiderations, as all ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour and covet this the moſt happy condition of life, and many men are much wanting to their own perfection, the Service of God, and of the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who, out of neglect to this gift, and not out of, or from, any ſtrength of temptation caſt themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the impediments of marriage, and might receive it, and do not: ſo I conceive it is <hi>not ſo ſafe for any, who are not very well practiſed firſt in mortification,</hi> and experience in much piety and devotion, <hi>to vow it. Not ſafe;</hi> not out of any diffidence in God, as if he would be wanting in his aſſiſtance proportionable to our endeavour; but in reference to the fleſh, leſt it ſhould happen, in this chiefeſt piece of its ſtrength, if we do not find that we have a ſtrong command
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:101527:22"/>over our ſelves, to overmaſter us; and our good reſolution become a ſnare to us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.35. <hi>beginning to build, and not able to finiſh.</hi> In which S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s warineſs may be a ſufficient precedent to ours; who, * finding the young widows after ſuch purpoſes (by their own fault indeed) remarrying, and * conſidering the greatneſs of internal and external temptations incident to youth, (thro the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent diſcipline the infancy of the Church was then capable of, not ſo reſtrained as latter times have ſince provided,) ordered that none under <hi>ſixty</hi> ſhould be admitted into publick ſervice upon ſuch ſtrict bonds and obligations. And indeed in the buſineſs of continency, in which ſome degree of burning is in the moſt pure, it is very hard, till long experience hath as it were aſſured us, at any one time exactly to meaſure our own ſtrength, conſtancy, and ſtedfaſtneſs, whether we ſhall be able to contain for the time to come; and, by the intervening of new temptations <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (unleſs we reſolve wholly to ſhut up our ſelves from them) our future, is not eaſily judged by our preſent, complexion. And as, when I look at the heavenlineſs of a ſingle life, I would adviſe all men to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain; ſo when at the great difficulty of ſuch a purity, as ſhall not be contaminated with one uncleanneſs, than which the Apoſtle adviſeth rather to marry, I would counſel all men to marry; [See <hi>Conf.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> how S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> complains of his parents not prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by marriage the many exorbitances of his wanton youth:] ſeeing the ſingle perſon much hazards a great ſin, whilſt he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts as great a glory. But yet the zealous Servant of God <hi>can do all thro Chriſt that strengthneth him. Nor ſhall he</hi> in this <hi>be tempted above his power,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.13. if he firſt tempt not himſelf; and the reward is well worthy the pains.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <p n="12">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>27</label>
                  <note place="margin">Yet not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for the Church, and very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial, to reſtrain the ſacred fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Miniſtry to ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note>XII. <hi>Tis not only lawful, but of ſingular benefit, that thoſe offices more neerly converſant about the publick ſervice of God,</hi> or the Church, <hi>ſhould be diſcharged only by ſingle perſons, wholly ſequeſtred from the world.</hi> Which if the Apoſtle ſaw fitting in the miniſtring <hi>widows,</hi> the <hi>Deaconeſſes,</hi> (Rom. 16.1.) how much more is it in the Clergy? Tho he, loth to lay ſuch a hard burden on the tender ſhoulders of the Infancy of the Church, therefore nouriſhed by him with <hi>milk, rather than ſtrong meat;</hi> * when there was not ſo much choice of Paſtors, and they of neceſſity to be admitted to ſuch fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions much ſooner than the widows; and * when ſingle life and Eunuchiſm was as yet, eſpecially to the Jew, a ſtrange propoſal, (which may partly be the reaſon, why he, who <hi>became all things to all men,</hi> in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. recommends ſingle life ſo modeſtly,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:101527:23"/>and after the way of delivering only his <hi>advice and judgment,</hi> (a phraſe unuſual in his other doctrines,) ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.6, 8. compared with the 10, 25, 40,) reſtrained then the Clergy only to one wife. Yet (where there is ſufficient plenty of ſingle perſons that are worthy, and not elſe) it ſeems no way unlawful or unjuſt, if the Church (which is * in this left to her liberty (for S. <hi>Paul,</hi> reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Clergy only to one wife, obligeth them not by this, to have a wife) and * hath power to eſtabliſh what the H. Scriptures no way prohibit) ſhall ordain (which is a means to make many more zealous of this excellent gift) * that ſingle perſons only ſhall be admitted into ſuch employments, or at leaſt into thoſe functions amongſt theſe of the more eminency and moment; and if theſe perſons ſhould afterward engage in marriage, * that they ſhall no longer ſtay in the ſame office. Which wiſdom, ſince the world frequently ſhews in many other places of leſs conſequence, they cannot be excuſed for omitting it in the Church-affairs, to which it is moſt proper.</p>
               <p>Neither do I ſee what hurt or ſcandal can come thereof, if on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Eccleſiaſtical Canons were ſtrictly executed: 1. If none, but after long probation of their temperance, continency, gravity, mortification, were admitted into ſuch ſacred employments, (ſee what tryal the Apoſtle requires before ſuch admiſſion, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and elſewhere, <hi>[not a novice, leſt he fall into the temptation of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; one of a good report,</hi> and found <hi>blameleſs;</hi> even the <hi>Deacons to be proved, before they uſe that office,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.10.]) 2. If all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary reſtraints from the ordinary occaſions and temptations of incontinency were uſed to ſuch perſons after admitted. 3. If the Church'es cenſures were vigorouſly executed againſt the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
               <p>Elſe, as Celibacy is better than Marriage, ſo Marriage is always honourable; but unchaſt celibacy, eſpecially in the Miniſters of Chriſt, moſt abominable, and for ever void of excuſe. And even after ſuch vows, (in which <hi>petenti dabitur, nec patietur Deus nos ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra id quod poſſumus tentari,</hi>) yet if ſuch a one will not contain, I conceive (ſuppoſing no Eccleſiaſtical law to intervene, which may render marriage to ſuch, when contracted, invalid, or not to be a marriage) he ſins much leſs in marrying, <hi>i. e.</hi> in doing a thing in it ſelf lawful, but againſt his vow, than in fornication, <hi>i.e.</hi> in doing a thing eternally unlawful, being againſt God's command: for the one fault is againſt God's law, the other only againſt his own. And if ſome, in comparing marriage with ſome one act of fornication or uncleaneſs, may affirm the firſt to be more oppoſite to a vow,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101527:23"/>than the latter; as rendring one uncapable of obſerving his vow at all for the future, which the latter doth not: yet in this all will agree, that even to a Votary the living in Marriage, than living in continual Fornication, or other uncleaneſs, is a life to God leſs of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive. S. <hi>Auſtin de Bono Viduitatis,</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> —<hi>Non quia ipſae nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae vel talium,</hi> i.e. <hi>voventium, damnandae judicantur, ſed damnatur propoſiti fraus, damnatur fracta voti fides,</hi> &amp;c. —<hi>Poſtremo damnantur tales, non quia conjugalem fidem poſterius inierant, ſed quia continentiae primam fidem irritam fecerunt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
